<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A supplication to the Kings most excellent Maiestie wherein, seuerall reasons of state and religion are briefely touched: not vnworthie to be read, and pondered by the lords, knights, and burgeses of the present Parliament, and other of all estates. Prostrated at his Highnes feete by true affected subiects.</title>
            <author>Colleton, John, 1548-1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107663</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843360</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843360</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8085</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8085)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 740:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A supplication to the Kings most excellent Maiestie wherein, seuerall reasons of state and religion are briefely touched: not vnworthie to be read, and pondered by the lords, knights, and burgeses of the present Parliament, and other of all estates. Prostrated at his Highnes feete by true affected subiects.</title>
                  <author>Colleton, John, 1548-1635.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Colleton.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Variant: with errata on G2v.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8085:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8085:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SVPPLICATION to the Kings moſt excellent <hi>Maiestie,</hi> Wherein, ſeuerall reaſons of State and Religion are briefely touched: not vnworthie to be read, <hi>and pondered by the Lords, Knights,</hi> and Burgeſes of the preſent Parliament, and other of all eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prostrated</hi> At his Highnes feete by true affected Subiects.</p>
            <q>Nos credimus, propter quod &amp; loquimur.</q>
            <bibl>2. Cor. 4. 13.</bibl>
            <q>Wee beleeue, for the which cauſe wee ſpeake alſo.</q>
            <figure/>
            <p>1604.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8085:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8085:2"/>
            <head>Most high and mightie Prince, and our deereſtly beloued Soueraigne.</head>
            <p>SO many cauſes concurre, whereſoeuer wee turne our thoughtes, and theſe moſt great, of reioycing, as we know not with which we ſhould begin the count, nor on which to ground our chiefeſt ioy. Your Maieſties direct title to the Imperiall Crowne of the Realme, both by lineall deſcent, and prioritie of blood, and your Highneſſe moſt quiet acceſſe to the ſame (Gods onely worke, aboue the expectation of man) doe, (as by moſt right they ſhould,) exceedingly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe and englad our heartes: Alſo the thrice fortunate vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the two Kingdomes (which not ſeldome in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times haue beene much infeſtuous one to the other) and this after ſo ſweete a meane, as by rightfull deuoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both Scepters to the immediate iſſue of either Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cannot but in ſemblable proportion multiplie and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce our ioyes; nor can wee any way doubt, but that the ſtrength of the Monarchy (now made inuincible by the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) will euer be moſt able to preſerue theſe our ioyes vnto vs, and make them perpetual, either kingdom being ſuch a fortres and countermure to other, and both ſo abounding with men and ſhipping, as no forrayne enemie, how potent ſoeuer, vnles hee firſt be weary of his owne fortunes, dare euer aduenture to offend or picke quarrel vnto: Likewiſe the hope and ſtrongeſt affiance which your Maieſties raigne ouer both nations yeelds, of reducing the bordurers of eyther Countrey to Chriſtian order: of turning to commodity the vaſt quantity of ground, which, by reaſon of the ſauage demeanor among them, hath,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8085:3"/> time out of minde layne waſte and vnoccupyed: and of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying peace, commerce and trafficke with all Nations, a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing moſt ſoueraigne, and which already is lighted on vs in good meaſure: Then, the vnſpeakable benefite of your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe fitte yeeres to gouerne, and your long and ſucceſſefull experience in the affaire, being the Arte of Artes, and office of God, farre more intricate, difficult and comberſome than any other kind of miniſtration, or ſtate of life on earth: Then alſo the ſpeciall conſolation which all men take in your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties regardefull loue toward the Nobilitie of the Realme, as hauing already reſtored ſome to their loſt dignities, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed others with honor and authoritie in State: Laſtly, to omit other infinite particulars of leſſe moment, the good trial of your Highneſſe proweſſe, wiſedome, iudgement, clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, bountie, compaſſion, the edification of your exemplar life (of like force to your ſubiectes for faſhioning their maners therevnto, as were the twigges of party colour, which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch <hi>Iacob</hi> laid before the flocke of ſheepe hee had in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, at the time of their conceyuing,) the nobleſt diſpoſition<note place="margin">Geneſ. 30. 38.</note> of our yong Prince and his brother, the rare vertues of their Queene-mother, our moſt reſpected Princeſſe, and the hope of ſuch ſtore of children from both your bodies, as may to the worlds end moſt renowmedly ſpread and perpetuate the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all coniunction, name, and family: We ſay, all theſe, and other like gratious reſpects doe ſo aboundantly repleniſh our hearts with ioy, as no temporall thing can more in the world. And to the end theſe our ioyes may euer inhabite in our ſoules proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſly without change or diminution, we your Maieſties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently affectionate ſubiectes, doe proſtrately beſeech your moſt Princely conſideration, to commiſerate our grieuous and long indured preſſures for confeſſing the Catholike Romaine faith; the all onely meane (as we vndoubtedly beleeue) of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing our ſoules eternally.</p>
            <p>We doe not preſume (our dread Soueraigne) to begge the allowance of ſome fewe Churches, for the exerciſe of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, nor yet the allotting of any Eccleſiaſtical liuing towards
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8085:3"/> the maintayning of the Paſtors of our Soules (a benefite that is not denyed by the Princes and State politique of other Countries, where diuerſitie of religion is tolerated, and infinite good found to ariſe thereof,) but the onely degree of fauour that we ſeeke at your Maieſties handes in this caſe, is, that out of your Princely compaſſion, you woulde bee pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe the penall lawes, enacted by our late Soueraigne againſt Catholike beleeuers, and to licence the practiſe of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in priuate houſes, without moleſtation to Prieſt or lay Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the ſame. For this (moſt gratious Prince) we intreat, for this wee ſhall euer continue our humble petitions, and the ſuite being (as our faith aſſureth vs) for the not aboliſhing of Gods nobleſt cauſe and honour vpon earth, and no wayes againſt the peace, ſtrength, or ſafetie of the Kingdome, but rather much conuenient (if haply not neceſſary) for the good preſeruation thereof, and alſo, for that the obtayning of the ſuite would bring vnſpeakeable renowme to your Maieſtie, with all the chiefeſt Rulers of the Chriſtian world, and endleſſe comforte to thouſands (who otherwayes liuing againſt their conſcience, muſt needes abide in continuall horrour of Soule) wee cannot thinke it a breach of duetie and leſſe thinke it a point of diſloyaltie, euer lowly to ſolicite, yea petitionarily to importune your Maieſtie, for the happie graunt of ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, farre-ſpeading and vniuerſall a bleſſedneſſe. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee would not be thought to ſpeake vnaduiſedly in the premiſſes, we craue leaue of your gratious Maieſtie to adioyne a fewe briefe reaſons for remonſtrance of that which is ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The world knoweth that there are three kinds of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in the Realme, the Proteſtant, the Puritane, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikely affected, and by generall report, the ſubiect Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely affected is not inferiour to the Proteſtant or Puritane, either in number, or alliance, or generoſitie of ſpirit and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. Which multitude or third kinde of ſubiects, would through the benefite of the diſpenall vſe or toleration of their religion, hold themſelues infinitely obliged to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and be ready in all occurrences very willingly to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8085:4"/> their liues and laſt drop of blood in any ſeruice ſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the defence of your Maieſties perſon, crowne, or dignitie: whereas being debarred of the ſaid fauor and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of conſcience (in which conſiſteth the true comfort of ſoule, and all Chriſtian corage) they muſt be forcibly driuen to lament their hard fortunes, to lie groaning vnder their croſſes, and conſequently without ſpirit or forwardneſſe in action, vnapt for any imployment, as perſons ouerwhelmed with griefe and deſolation of their moſt piteous and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe, the Puritane, as he increaſeth dailie aboue the Proteſtant in number, ſo is he of a more preſuming, imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and hotter diſpoſition and zeale, euer ſtrongly burning in deſire to reduce all things to the forme of his owne Idaea, or imagination conceiued, and therefore by diſcourſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not vnlike (the enterpriſe being to be paralleled by many examples) to attempt the ouerthrow of the Proteſtant, and bring the kingdome, eſpecially the Eccleſiaſticall ſtate to a paritie or popular forme of gouernement, if the Catholike (perchaunce the powerableſt let thereof) were once extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: and to extinguiſh him, no meane more potent, than to forbid and puniſh the exerciſe of his religion. And what confuſion, hauocke, and effuſion of blood ſuch an attempt would worke in the commonweale, it is eaſie to coniecture, whiles the Puritane with his complices, and ſuch as thirſt (an infinite number) to haue matters in ſcuffling, to impugne on the one ſide, and the Biſhops, Deanes, Canons, and the greateſt poſſeſſors of Spirituall liuings, with all thoſe that do adhere to them, defend on the other ſide, and either partie ſtiffely and violently perſecuting other, as is the cuſtome in ſuch commotions, without regard of God or country. Which diſaſtrous and moſt deadly miſchiefe can not in probability approach, or euer growe to head, ſo long as the Catholike findeth fauour with your Maieſtie, in enioying the free vſe of his religion. Or put caſe the Puritane ſhould euer aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to make ſuch an attempt, yet the oddes againſt him (he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8085:4"/> hauing two ſorts of aduerſaries, the Proteſtant, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikely affected by the foreſaid fauor) are much much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any way in reaſon or likelihood the victorie may be iuſtly doubted of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Moreouer, toleration of Catholike religion ſeemeth very conuenient for ſtrengthning and ſecuring your Maieſty againſt all worldly attempts foraine and domeſticall. Againſt forraine, in reſpect the cauſe why any ſuch trouble ſhould be once intended, muſt needes be in all probabilitie the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Catholike religion, which pretext or cauſe is quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued by your Maieſties graunt of the free exerciſe thereof. Or if it ſhould fall out, that notwithſtanding the happineſſe of the ſaid moſt ſoueraigne fauour, any forraine Prince, or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces confederated, either on enuie of your Maieſties greatneſſe, or vpon feare of what conſequence the vnion of the three Kingdomes might prooue in time, ſhould be ſo intemperate, as either to incite companies within the Realme, or inuade vpon the aboue named pretence, no doubt but all Catholikes would eftſoone diſcloſe the practiſe, and moſt willingly ſtraine the vttermoſt of all their poſſible forces and reſiſtaunce for withſtanding the ſaid enterpriſe, made by whomſoeuer, and vnder what ſhadow of title or authoritie ſoeuer. And if inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine warre or any vproare ſhould happen thorow any diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie of the ſubiect or other accident, there can be likewiſe no doubt (the Catholike religion teaching all temporall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Princes, and more ſeuerely cenſuring and puniſhing all ſortes of rebellion, then doth either the Puritane, or the Proteſtant doctrine) but that all Catholikes would preſently flocke to the banner of your Maieſtie, and with the effuſion of their beſt bloud firſt guarde and protect your royall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and then defend all and ſingular your Highneſſe rightes and prerogatiues. A bounden duety, as our ſelues doe right willingly acknowledge, and the contrary a moſt deteſtable and treaſonable offence, neuertheleſſe the readineſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of our ſeruices heerein can not but increaſe your Maieſties ſtrength and ſafetie of the Crowne and Realme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8085:5"/> the things we deſire to haue beleeued, and would remonſtrate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Furthermore, both the auntient Philoſophers and the Stateſ-men of latter time doe write, and common ſenſe proclaymeth, that the glory, puiſſaunce and ſtableneſſe of a kingdome, conſiſt more in the true vertue and goodneſſe, than in the ſtore and multitude of ſubiectes; becauſe vertue begetteth glory, and is the cheriſher of fortitude, both which diſdaine nothing more than treachery, and baſeneſſe of mind, the common Slewces which conuey into all eſtates all that is diſhonourable. And it is ſeldome, if euer ſeene (moſt noble King) that they who are conſtant, obedient and faithfull to God in the religion they beleeue, are not likewiſe true, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectiue, and faithfull to their King in all duties appertaining. For as grace, the feare of ſinne, and the loue of heauen doe worke them to the performing of the one; ſo will the ſame grace, feare and loue (the neglect being of equall damage in both) induce them to obſerue the other. Nay, they both are ſo neerely allied, depend ſo abſolutely one of the other, and are alike eſſentially lincked together, as the one can not be either laudably or indifferently fulfilled, and the other not accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>How conſtant and faithfull the Catholike hath carried himſelfe in the religion hee profeſſeth, it appeareth by this, that neither the paying of twenty pounds a moneth, only for not going to the Proteſtants church, or where his ability could not affoord ſo much, there the leeſing of two partes of his liuings, and the vtter forfeiture of all his goodes, nor making of Prieſtes (the feeders of their ſoules) to be traitors, and their receiuers, felons (lawes and penalties that neuer had ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of inſtance or preſident in the world) either did or could make him to denie, or exteriorly to diſguiſe his religion, or relinquiſh to practiſe it: proofes, in all vnderſtanding moſt ſufficient to conuince, that he dreadeth God, feareth to offend his conſcience, and that he chriſtianly ſeekes to ſaue his ſoule. And if ſo, then as we thinke there cannot iuſtly be made any doubt, but that he will likewiſe ſhew himſelfe obedient and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8085:5"/> duetifull to his Soueraigne in all things that belong to tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall alegeance, or wherein ſoeuer the omiſſion may taint or endanger the ſafetie of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Of that which is ſaid, wee would, vnder your Maieſties gratious leaue, inferre, that the Catholike ſubiect is (if any other) the glory, ſtrength and perpetuitie of the Kingdome, becauſe he principally ſeeking heauen in this world, and will not for the worlde be diuerted, cannot be treacherous or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall, or vnduetifull to your Highneſſe, but in euery ſeruice, and diſtreſſe occurring, valiant, reſolute and moſt faithfull. By which it ſeemeth manifeſt, that if the Lawes of our deceaſed Queene ſhould not be repealed; but more, if they ſhould be re-eſtabliſhed (a rigor which in it ſelfe preſently imbarketh vs into all calamities) alas your Grace doth not only thereby depriue your Imperiall crowne and realme of the beſt meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting affections, and ſuppreſſingly diſable thoſe your ſubiects, who otherwiſe woulde for their qualities ſtand your Maieſtie and their Country in good ſeruice, and do much long for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to make knowne their readineſſe that waye; but your Highneſſe by the ſame ſhall alſo giue occaſion to the frailer ſort, of aduenturing their Soules to euerlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, by diſſembling their faith and religion. Which incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and vnmanly part of theirs, how little credite or reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ought to bring vnto them, or is cauſe of truſt to your Maieſtie, wee leaue that prudent and heroicall example to informe your Highnes, which <hi>Nicephorus</hi> and others record<note place="margin">Niceph. li. 6. cap. 35.</note> of the Emperor <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> who ſeeing a ſpeciall minion of his to haue changed his religion, thereby to pleaſe and wind himſelfe into greater fauor, iudged him to loſe his head, ſaying, <hi>Si Deo fidem ſinceram non ſeruasti, quomodo mihi qui homo ſum, conſcientiam ſanam praestabis?</hi> Thou that haſt violated thy faith with God, how is it poſſible thou ſhouldeſt keepe thy fidelitie with me being a man?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Beſides, the good that to our vnderſtanding, would redound to your Highnes, and the whole realme, by the grant of a toleration, is manifolde and very great, for that the ſame
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8085:6"/> could not but begett and foſter a right earneſt and zealous aemulation, or holy ſtrife among your Maieſties ſubiectes, differing in religion, who ſhould exceed the other in dutie, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and loue towardes your perſon and affaires, whiles euery one enioyed the freedome of his conſcience, a meane of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers moſt likely to make your owne ſtate and perſon very ſecure, renowneable and bleſſed: your kingdomes opulent, peacefull and inuincible: your ſubiectes ſtudious, ſeruiceable and louing, and in all imployments preſſing to ſurpaſſe one the other in care and diligence. Then the which, nothing can be thought that is either more happy, more glorious, or more generall, and which earthly heauen, if it be any other way to bee attained, it ſeemeth ſooneſt, by graunting a toleration of religion, and by indifferently preferring the Profeſſors, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to euery mans deſert, quality and ſufficiencie: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all beeing in this manner intereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in your Graces fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and vnpartially taſting the ſweete thereof, can not be but all faſteſt vnited in the defence of the Realme, and in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt ſafegarde of your Maieſties perſon, crowne and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Neither would toleration of Catholike religion bleſſe your Maieſtie and all your ſeuerall Dominions, with the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines praecedent onely, but the ſame woulde alſo inuite all the Catholike Kings and Rulers in Chriſtendome (being incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably more in number and potencie, than are the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, Puritane and Lutheran Potentates) to ſeeke and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a true and reall league, both of peace and amitie with your Highneſſe (the ſourſe and ſelfe life of princely felicitie:) and make your Maieſties choiſe of matches for your children farre more noble, rich and ample, in regarde no Catholique Prince will refuſe to entertaine, yea to ſue for like treatie, where toleration of his Religion, is by Royall aſſent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is affirmed in holy Writte, that <hi>Mercy and Trueth preſerue the King, and his Throne is establiſhed by clemencie;</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowances,<note place="margin">Pro. 20. 28.</note> which before they were written, the great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8085:6"/> 
               <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> well obſerued and truſted vnto. For ruling ouer many nations, and hauing ſubdued the whole earth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his dominion, concluded neuertheleſſe with himſelfe (as it is read in the booke of <hi>Esther) To gouerne his ſubiects with clemencie and lenitie</hi> And the reaſon is plaine, for that the loue<note place="margin">Ca. 13. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the ſubiectes (ſooneſt and moſt wonne by theſe vertues) is the ſtrongeſt Caſtell in the world, an army if any other, moſt puiſſant, and a bulwarke inexpugnable. And as nothing can ſit ſo neere a chriſtian mans Soule, as the religion he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: ſo vndoubtedly no mercie, no clemencie, no lenitie, of what nature, or in what matter ſoeuer, can reliſh ſo ſweete, ſo laſtingly gratefull, ſo forcibly binding, raviſhing and as it were, coniuring the hearts of ſubiects, as doth the mercy and benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which is ſhewed in licenſing freedome of conſcience, and the exerciſe of their religion. So that by permiſſion of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion (a religion, that of all other kindes of religion, hath moſt and woorthieſt Profeſſours in other Kingdomes that next border vpon your Highneſſe, and neither the leaſt, nor meaneſt ſort of ſubiectes within your owne realme) your Maieſtie may make millions in and without your territories, ſo entirely and affectionately deuoted to your perſon, crowne and poſterity, as no attempt, no danger, no tumult can ariſe, wherein your ſacred Maieſtie ſhall not finde preſent and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureſt harbour.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In few wordes, for that we are loath to bee tedious to your Maieſty, in multiplying of reaſons, beſide the pleading of theſe and other like regardefull Motiues that might bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, which doe all directly ſtand for toleration, wee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinke (vnder your Maieſties correction) that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the libertie wee intreate, is, neyther in reaſon of State, a thing hurtfull, nor by the doctrine of Proteſtants vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to be granted. The firſt is cleare by the example of <hi>Germanie, Fraunce, Poland,</hi> &amp; other Countries, where diuerſitie of religion is licenced by ſupreame authoritie, &amp; the like ſound peace, wrought and eſtabliſhed thereby, as both make the ſaide Dominions and Territories to floriſh, and coulde neuer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8085:7"/> (though oft laboured) be brought to paſſe by force of warre or bloud-ſhed. The other likewiſe is as little doubtfull, if not better knowne, the Proteſtants bookes, their Pulpits, their priuate writings, and Diſcourſes ſounding nothing more, (whilſt they had not the Sword and Scepter on their ſide) then that it was vnlawfull, tyrannicall, yea diabolicall, and antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianlike to puniſh any for matter of meere conſcience, faith and religion. And the fauour wee ſue for, is but the benefite of that poſition which they held for moſt true and ſcripturall: ſo that if they ſhould now depart from that doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, they muſt needs giue the world to ſee, that either then they did wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly mainetaine the poſition againſt truth, onely to ſerue their owne turne withall (an ingrauen blemiſh) or generally er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in that poynt of doctrine (a blot of no leſſe diſcredite vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them) which breathing clemencie, did moſt recommend, and gaue greateſt increaſe to their religion.</p>
            <p>And if the Petition we proſtrate, and do moſt ſuppliantly begge of your Maieſtie, be neither preiudiciall to matter of State, nor repugnant to the doctrine of the religion eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and regnant in the kingdome, as the proofes afore going ſeeme to make plaine, wee hope there is no other exception that can iuſtly impeach, and many ſeuerall reſpects that may much further the obtaining of our requeſt at your Graces handes. The religion, that vnder your Highneſſe fauour, we ſue to haue tolerated, is the ſelfe ſame religion, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to which our country was conuerted<note place="margin">An. Dom. 596. by S. Austen the Monke, and our Apostle, ſent hither by Saint Gregorie the great Pope of Rome. Beda de gestis Anglorum libr. 1. cap. 23.</note> from Paganiſme, and which, both all the chriſtian kings of our nation (<hi>Edward</hi> the 6. a childe, only excepted) and alſo all your Highneſſe predeceſſors in the crowne of Scotland, euer publikely profeſſed, and for the zealous maintenaunce whereof, your Maieſties great grandfather <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth, was worthily ſurnamed <hi>Protector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. A religion which by the teſtimonies of all Antiquitie <note n="*" place="margin">This apeareth by Mermannus in ſuo Theatro, the Magdeburgenſes in tit. de propagatione, Baronis and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Collectors of Antiquitie.</note> was the primary religion that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8085:7"/> euer any heathen Nation, conuerted chriſtian, did profeſſe: and the Wiſdome of heauen commaundeth, <hi>not to tranſgreſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 28.</note> 
               <hi>the antient bounds which our Fathers appointed,</hi> but contrarily, <hi>to abide in that which we heard from the beginning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>3. A religion, of whoſe communion and felowſhippe the founders of other religions, or the reformers of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches faith (if they more deſire to be ſo called) were once, and went out; and conſequently their doctrine newer, and leſſe auncient then ours: and therefore as we beleeue, not <hi>the good</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſeede,</hi> but <hi>the cockle that was ſowen after.</hi> And that wee neuer going out of any knowne chriſtian ſocietie (for the whole world can not tell your Grace out of what church we depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when, how, and where) as did the former, the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall markes of falſe beleeuers, namely, <hi>To goe out from others;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 19. Iude v. 19. Rom. 16. 17.</note> 
               <hi>To ſegregate themſelues,</hi> and <hi>To make diſſenſions and ſcandalls, contrary to the doctrine they had learned,</hi> can not belong to vs by any poſſible application, nor by any ſleight or deuiſe ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from them.</p>
            <p>4. A religion whoſe firſt Inſtituters, except Chriſt and his Apoſtles, or after-deuiſers cannot be named by any of our Aduerſaries, nor can they all ſhew that peece or fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall point of our faith, either of late, or ſithence the Apoſtles time defined, which <note n="*" place="margin">This is witneſſed in the Councel of Epheſus in epistola Synodi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Nestorium, in the Councel of Calcedon, act. 4, 5, &amp; 6. Item ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali 6. act. 4. &amp; 10. &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. 7. act. 2. And by Athanaſ. of the Nicen. Councel in epist. ad Afros, &amp; in epist. de Synodis Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini &amp; Seleuciae. And by Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Councel of Alexandria in historia eccleſiast. lib. 1. ca. 5. and others.</note> was not formerly beleeued, and the contrary thereof neuer taught by the Romane Church. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in our vnderſtanding it is euident, that the religion we profeſſe, is not, as it is ſlandered to be, a deuiſe or inuention of man, nor euer was contrary to it ſelfe in doctrine; but whatſoeuer hath beene in latter ages explicitiuely defined, the ſame was alwayes, not only holden true from the beginning in our church, but alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitiuely beleeued for the infallible au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie thereof.</p>
            <p>5. A religion, that hath confuted and outlaſted ſeuerall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8085:8"/> hundreds of hereſies, which manifoldly diuided in themſelues,<note place="margin">488. after Prateolus account.</note> did yet euer giue hands to the ouerthrow of this one, but neuer found other rocke than it, on which they were broken, or tooke their confuſion by. Which ſeemeth infallibly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, <hi>That the weapons of our Churches warrefare, are not</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10. 4.</note> 
               <hi>carnall,</hi> but (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writeth of the true doctrine) <hi>mighty to God, vnto the destruction of munitions, destroying Counſells, and all loftineſſe, extolling it ſelfe against the knowledge of God.</hi> And that our church and religion euer conquering their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors, and neuer conquered by them, is that kingdome which the Prophet ſaieth, <hi>Shall breake in peeces and conſume</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 44.</note> 
               <hi>all other kingdomes, and it ſelfe ſtand for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. A religion, that erected and built all the Churches, Hoſpitalles and ancient Colleges in Chriſtendome, indowed them with liuings, inſtituted the Vniuerſities and Seminaries, diſtinguiſhed the multitude into pariſhes, proportioned the Tithes, annexed the glebeland, founded the Biſhoprickes, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited the Dioceſes, decreed Eccleſiaſticall lawes and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, enacted all the olde Lawes of our Realme, and did (for that they would not <hi>be vacant without fruit,</hi> as the Apoſtle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>in the knowledge of our Lorde Ieſus</hi>) a thouſand good woorkes beſides, of which the religion regnant reapeth daily benefite, and could not without ſuch our churches prouiſion and ordinaunces, euer haue carried the exterior ſhew it doth.</p>
            <p>7. A religion, that in three ages together had not three<note place="margin">9, 10, &amp; 11. Centenaries.</note> open aduerſaries in the chriſtian worlde, who contradicted or impugned her doctrine, or beleeued another forme of faith, then that which ſhe then and now teacheth. And the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the eternall God (alluding to his Church) affirmeth, that <hi>in the multitude of people conſisteth the glory of a King; and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 28. Gloſſa inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin. in hunc locum.</note> 
               <hi>in the ſmall number, the ignominy of the Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8. A religion, whoſe chiefe profeſſors and ſpreaders thereof to other Nations were alwayes of a knowne holy life, and ſemblable death, and the protoparents of all other religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, men of a much contrary note: and we are ſure by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony<note place="margin">Matt. 7. 20.</note> of Gods word, that <hi>the good and bad tree are to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8085:8"/> knowne by their fruites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>9. A religion, to which the famouſeſt <note n="a" place="margin">Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Magnus, Iauianus with aboue fortie Emperours of the East. Maiorianus, Carolus Magnus, with full neere fortie other Emperours of the Weast.</note> Emperours and <note n="b" place="margin">Clodoueus, Childibertus with aboue threeſcore Kings of Fraunce. Ranimirus, Sanctius, with almost twenty other Kings of Aragon. Pelagius, Faſila, with at least fortie other Kings of Castile. Alphonſus, Sanctius, with many moe Kings of Portugall. Geyza, Stephanus, with aboue thirtie Kings of Hungary. Beſides the Kings of Polonia, Bohemia, Denmarke, Norway, Suetheland, Gothland, Dalmatia, Baiorta, Germania, Alemannia, Morauia, Loraine, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy, Prouince, Lomberdy, Italy, Naples, Sicily, Sardinia, Nauarre: and the Kings of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frike, as of Aethiopia, Nubia, and others. Likewiſe the Kings of Canaria, Manicongus, Beno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potama, Angola, Guinea, Bentoninus, Quiloa, Melinda, Mozambique; the Kings of Aſia, as of Ciprus, Armenia, Hieruſalem, Tartaria, and ſome Kings of the Agarens and Saracens: many Kings of the Heruleans, Iberians, Alanes, Abaſgorians, Lazorians, Scithians, Perſians, and others.</note> Kings of the world haue bowed their Crownes, <note n="c" place="margin">As Conſtantinus Magnus Emperour, Dagobertus, Carolus, S. Ludouicus, and other Kings of Fraunce. Alphonſus, Ranimirus, Alphonſus the great, Ranimirus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Alphonſus 6. with other Kings of Spaine. Stephanus and Ladiſlaus Kings of Hungary. Miſcelſtaus, Bole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaus, Caſimirus ſanctus, and Caſimirus Magnus Kings of Polonia, and many moe Kings of other Nations.</note> preſented their giftes, <note n="d" place="margin">As Iustinus Emperour, the perſon of Pope Iohn. Iustinianus of Pope Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, King Pipin the perſon of Pope Stephen the ſecond: Carolus of Pope Leo the third<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udoui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us of Sergius the ſecond, and of Pope Nicholas: Henry the fourth of Pope Paſchal the ſecond, and others.</note> reuerenced her Prelates, <note n="e" place="margin">As Philippus Arabs Emperour, the Cenſure of Pope Fabian. Euſeb. lib. 6. ca. 27. hiſtor. eccl. the Emperor Theo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſius the excommunication of S. Ambr. Theodoret. lib. 5. cap. 17. hist. eccl. Sozom. lib. 7. ca. 24. the Emperour Otho the third, the inioyned penaunce of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mualdus Abbat. Petr. Dam. in vita Romual. To which may be added the deuoute readineſſe of Henry the ſecond, to accept and fulfill the ſentence of Pope Alexanders Legates, touching the death and murthering of Saint Thomas of Canterburie, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubrigenſ. libr. 2. cap. 25.</note> obeyed their cenſures, yea and hath at this preſent many of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt monarchs and potentates on earth to her Profeſſors, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and foſter-fathers: So as of the Romane Religion onelie, theſe enſuing paſſages and propheticall praedictions of holie Scripture muſt, of force, take their verification, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as yet (being the latter yeares or euening of the Church) vnfulfilled: <hi>The Gentiles ſhall feare thy name, O Lord, and all the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 101. 16. Pſal. 71. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Kings of the earth thy glory.</hi> Againe, <hi>All Kings of the earth ſhall adore him, all Nations ſhall ſerue him.</hi> And in an other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,<note place="margin">Eſa. 49. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queenes thy Nurſes.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8085:9"/> And againe, <hi>Gentiles ſhall walke in thy light, and Kings in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 62. 3.</note> 
               <hi>brightneſſe of thy vpriſing.</hi> Places which to our iudgement moſt euidently conuince, that not onely ſome Kings of the earth ſhall profeſſe and cheriſh true religion, but that the greater number of all chriſtian Kings ſhall embrace and aduaunce the ſame. Now, it is moſt certaine, and as cleare as noone day, by all Antiquities, Proofes and Chronicles of the worlde, that there was neuer Emperour, nor till this age, any one King vnder heauen, that intertained or profeſſed Proteſtant religion.</p>
            <p>10. A religion, that from the firſt floure of her infancie euer had, and ſtill hath to her beleeuers, infinite multitudes of either ſexe, profeſſing Pouertie, Chaſtitie, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the three <note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 19. 21. marc. 19. 12. 1. cor. 7. 25. math. 16. 24.</note> chiefe Euangelicall counſelles obſerued of the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 27. Auguſt. de Ciuit. lib. 17. ca. 4. Hieron. lib. 1. contra Iouinia.</note> Apoſtles, practiſed by thoſe <note n="c" place="margin">Saint Anthony, Hilarion, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, Francis Dominike, Bernard, and thouſands moe.</note> who were counted of greateſt holineſſe, moſt highly commended by all <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <p>¶ <hi>Of Pouertie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hieron. epiſtola prima ad Heliod. ca. 6. item in cap. 19. Matth. &amp; ad Demetria. de ſeruanda virginitat. epiſt. 8. ca. 7. Quaeſt. ad Hedib. epiſt. 150. &amp; ad Pammachum ſuper obitu Paulinae epiſt. 26. ca. 3. &amp; 4. Baſil. quaeſt. 9. in regulis fuſius diſputat. Damaſcen. in hiſtor. Barlaam &amp; Ioſaph. ca. 15. Chryſ. in illud Pauli: Salutate Priſcam &amp; Aquilam.</p>
                  <p>¶ <hi>Of Chaſtitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hieron. in cap. 9. Matth. &amp; lib. 1. aduerſ. Iouin. ca. 7. Baſil. de virginitat. Epiphan. haereſi. 58. contra Valeſios. Aug. de virginitat. ca. 14. 24. &amp; ſequentibus. Greg. in tertiae parte Curae paſtora. admonit. 29. Ambroſ. &amp; Theodoretus in 1. Cor. 7. &amp; Amb. in epiſt. 83. ad Siricium Papam. &amp; 82. ad Vercellenſes. &amp; in tribus libris de Virginib. &amp; alibi. Damaſc. lib. 4. orthodoxae ſid. ca. 25. Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, Baſilius, Nazianzenus de Virgint. Fulgent. epiſt. 3. ad Probam. ca. 9. &amp; 10. Ignatius ad Philadelphi. Cipri. de bouo Pudicit. Iſodor. libr. 2. de ſum. bono. ca. 40. Caſſian. coll. 12. ca. 4. &amp; 7.</p>
                  <p>¶ <hi>Of Obedience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Aug. libr. 14. de Ciuit. ca. 12. Hieron. epiſt. 8. ad Demetriad. ca. 10. Greg. libr. 35. moral. ca. 12. &amp; in 1. Reg. li. 2. ca 4. li. 4. ca. 5. &amp; li. 6. ca. 2. Caſſian. li. 4. ca. 10 Collat. 2. ca. 11. &amp; Coll. 4. ca. 20. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. in ſerm. de 3. ordinib. eccle. item ad milites templi ca. 13. &amp; in ſerm. de virtut. obed. Baſil. de Constit. monaſt. ca. 23. Philo in lib. de vita contemplat. Ioſephus lib. 18. antiquit. ca. 2. Epiphan. haereſi 29. Dioniſius de Eccleſiaſt. Hierarchia. ca. 6. Euſeb. lib. 1 de demonſtrat. Euangelic. ca. 8. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzenu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> orat. 20. Athanaſ. in vita Anthonij. Sulpitius in vita Martini. Iſodor. li. 2. de eccleſ. officijs ca. 15. Sozomenus lib. 1. hist. ca. 12. Chryſost. aduerſ. Vituperatores monast. vitae &amp; Hom. 5. ad pop. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um ſequentibus, &amp; infiniti alij.</p>
               </note> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, not onely as diuine helpes to perfection, but alſo as beautifull ornaments in Chriſts Church, raiſing the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours to ſupreame degree of grace and glorie.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8085:9"/>
            <p>11. A religion that hath bene teſtified by the bloud and ſanctitie of ſuch Martirs and Confeſſors as our Aduerſaries themſelues allow of, and hold them glorious in heauen; and either all the points of her doctrine, or the moſt controuerted and weightieſt, witneſſed by euidence of moſt authenticall<note place="margin">Collected in part by <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbrachius, in ſuis collationib.</hi>
               </note> miracles, by the records of all ages, and by the diſcuſſing cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and approbation of general Counſels, the higheſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory on earth, and oracles of greateſt infallibility, as being the ſentences of all the beſt learned in the worlde aſſembled together, and holpen in the affaire by the <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 18. 20. &amp; 28. 20.</note> preſence of Chriſt our Sauiour, by the <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 14. 16. &amp; 16. 13. &amp; Act. 15. 20.</note> aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, and by <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 17. 17. Luk. 22. 31.</note> our Lords promiſe and prayer.</p>
            <p>12. A religion vnchanging and of admirable conſent in her doctrine, hauing euermore the ſame bounds of faith in all places, and not varying in euery countrie and ſtate as do other religions which haue not one ſupreame head, and an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged power to define, but make the letter of ſcripture (miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpretable by euery contentious ſpirit) the onely touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone and chiefe Iudge of all differences in faith, whereby ſo many opinions and formes of religion may be ſquared out, as there be priuate fancies raigning.</p>
            <p>13 A religion, which by the graunt of our Aduerſaries, hath had for the laſt thouſand yeeres and more, the cuſtodie of the ſacred Bible, of the Apoſtles, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Creede, and preſerued them from periſhing by Pagan, Iewe, or heretike: yea, and from whoſe handes or Treaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, the Religion nowe eſtabliſhed, not onely receiued all the partes of Scripture ſhe maketh vſe of; but alſo learned the forme of Chriſtening, Marrying, Churching of women, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the ſicke, Burying, and ſundry other like, as their books, tranſlated out of ours, doe declare. And therefore our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt needes be the elder. Nor can it bee tolde (as wee can eaſily tell all other ſortes of Religions) what former Societie we did euer ſupplant or inuade, or tooke from it, eyther our firſt poſſeſſion of the Scriptures, forme of Sacraments, or any other Eccleſiaſticall rites or ceremonies.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:8085:10"/>
            <p>14. A Religion, that inſtituted the feaſtes, the faſting dayes, and all the goodly ceremonies, and ſolemne obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are yet vſed (though many other pared away) and commaunded in the Proteſtant religion, as the feſtiuities of Chriſtmas, Eaſter, Aſcenſion, Whitſontide, and the Eues and feaſtes of the Apoſtles, likewiſe the faſtes of Lent, and Ember dayes, abſtinence on Fridayes and Saturdayes, much holeſome and very commodious to the Common-weale: Semblablie the rites and ſacred formes kept in Coronations, inſtallements, and in all other ſortes of ſolemnities, that carrie eyther ſtate, decency or veneration with them.</p>
            <p>15. A religion, that founded the Eccleſiaſticall cenſures, and ſortes of diſcipline, as ſuſpenſion, interdiction, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, irregularitie, degradation and the like, and was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the author of the Cannon lawe, ſtudied throughout the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Chriſtian world, and many pointes, both of her cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, lawes and diſcipline, practiſed by the Proteſtants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>16. A religion that onely hath canonized her profeſſors for Saintes after death, and celebrateth their annuall memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, whereby their names euer liue in honor, and all poſteritie incited both to glorifie God for his graces beſtowed on them, and alſo ſtudiouſly to imitate their vertues. Whereby that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeueration of the Prophet is verified, <hi>Thy friendes (ô God</hi>)<note place="margin">Pſal. 138. 17.</note> 
               <hi>are very much honoured of mee.</hi> Likewiſe that ſaying of <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiasticus</hi> fulfilled, <hi>Nations ſhall declare his wiſedome, and the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ca. 39. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Church ſpeake forth his praiſe:</hi> and alſo the rites of friendſhip and true loue obſerued, which is to loue our friends friend for our friendes ſake, and incomparably more the Saintes of God, for their and our loue towards God.</p>
            <p>17. A religion, whoſe refuſe and reuolted prieſtes are dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med lawefull and ſufficiently ordered to preach the worde of God, to miniſter Sacraments, and to exerciſe all ſpirituall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction in the proteſtant and Puritane Congregation. A proofe, which ſeemeth vnanſwerable, that our Church is the true Church: for were her doctrine falſe, ſhe teaching in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8085:10"/> pointes as ſhe doth, it muſt needes followe, that ſhee is the ſynagogue, if not the arch-ſynagogue of Sathan, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hath, nor can poſſibly haue (God and the diuell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo contrary) authoritie, to initiate and make lawfull and compleate Miniſters, for exerciſing ſpirituall faculties in the true Church. Neither is the Proteſtant Miniſter or Biſhop comming to our Catholike fraternitie (as many come of the firſt ſorte) reputed other then for meere lay men without orders.</p>
            <p>18. A religion, to whoſe antiquitie and veritie of moſt parte of her doctrine controuerſed, the faſhion of euery Church, Chappell, and Chancell, the recordes of euery Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall Colledge, and Abbey decayed, yea, euery auncient ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, church-window, and graue-ſtone, do bring and giue apparant euidence, as thinges all wearing her badges, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtifying her elder childrens faith, deuotion and pietie.</p>
            <p>19. A religion, whoſe groundes and foundation are ſo rockie and ſure, and the proofes and teſtimonies alike infinite, ample, aboundant, and vnanſwerable, as the Proteſtant him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aſſayled by the Puritane and other ſects, knowes not how to defend poſitions encountred, but by flying to the ſtrengths and impregnable arguments of the catholike Romane church and her doctors.</p>
            <p>20. A religion, that teacheth not <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 7. 13.</note> 
               <hi>the broade and large, but the narrow and ſtraite way,</hi> (ſuch as holy writte affirmeth the way to heauen to be) as annuall <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 20. 23.</note> confeſſion to a Prieſt, <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 6. 7. Matth. 32. and 11. 21. Mar. 1. 15. Luk. 13. 3. 2. Cor. 12. 21. Act. 1. 38. and 26. 20.</note> pennance, <note n="d" place="margin">Leuit. 5. 16. Luk. 19. 8.</note> reſtitution, <note n="e" place="margin">Ezech. 8. 30. Ioel. 2. 12. Matth. 3 8. Luk. 3. 8. 1. Cor. 11. 32.</note> ſatisfaction, preſcript, faſting dayes, ſet times of abſtinence, <note n="f" place="margin">Leui. 23. 21. Pſal. 75. 12. Eccleſ. 5. 3. 1. Tim. 5. 12.</note> performance of vowes, <note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 4, 5.</note> one vniforme ſtinte of faith, <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 8. 13. Coloſ. 3. 5.</note> mortification of the old man, and the like Iniunctions, neyther obſerued nor impoſed by other Religions, but rather libertie in their ſtead, and yet all of them directly and plainely preſcribed in holy Scripture, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept onely the appointment of preſcript time for confeſſion, faſting, and abſtinence, a power, and prerogatiue, left to the wiſedome and ordering of the Catholike Church; of whoſe Prelats our Sauior himſelf ſaith, <note n="i" place="margin">Luke 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>He that heareth you, heareth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8085:11"/> me, and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me.</hi> Which authoritie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo was giuen to the Biſhops of the olde Lawe, and of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence more to the chiefe Prelates of the new Law: <hi>He that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall waxe proude, refuſing to obey the commandement of the Prieſt, ſhall die by the decree of the Iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>21. A religion, for whoſe defence, the Title of <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> was firſt giuen to the Kinges of our Nation; the Title of <hi>Moſt Christian,</hi> to the kings of Fraunce, of <hi>Moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> to the kings of Spayne: the ſtill retayning of which Titles doth argue the allowance of her iuriſdiction. And there is no one of the auncient Fathers, who doth not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe wordes of the Prophet, to be onely meant of this Church, <hi>The Nation and Kingdome that will not ſerue thee, ſhall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 60. 12.</note> 
               <hi>periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>22. A religion, into whoſe ſocietie and profeſſion, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer truely entreth, by and by liueth in more awe of God, and feare of ſinne, and changeth his former life to the better: and of the other ſide, whoſoeuer leapeth out, and departeth from her fellowſhip and communion, beginneth incontinent to leade a worſe life, then whiles he liued her childe, and frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her Sacramentes. Of both which there bee ſtore of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and of the latter too many, verifying what is ſayd, and not vnknowne to thouſands, yea, the caſe is ſo familiar, as it is now growen into a Prouerbe with many: That the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant religion is good to liue in, but the Papiſt religion good to die in.</p>
            <p>23. A religion, which now hath, and had in all ages, the moſt famous men for wit, learning, reading, iudgement, vertue and true pietie (qualities, of all other, likelieſt to diſcerne and abandon error) to her Teachers and Doctors, and euer enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the like ſtore of ſuch lights, as our Oppoſitors had neuer reaſon to compare with, or if they do, the extant monuments in ſchoole, poſitiue, &amp; myſticall diuinitie, and in all other litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will quickly ſhewe the inequalitie and diſproportion of the compariſon.</p>
            <p>24. A Religion, whoſe publike, and Church ſeruice is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8085:11"/> executed with that maieſtie, honorable grauitie, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and the ſeuerall parts, and ceremonies thereof ſo aptly and admirablie compoſed, and ordred for annuall comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration, and repreſenting of our Sauiours incarnation, birth, life, paſſion, buriall, reſurrection, aſcenſion, of the comming downe of the Holy Ghoſt, of the myſterie of the Trinitie, and of other paſſages, as well of Chriſt our head, as of his members the Saincts, as it begetteth, feedeth, and reneweth ſingular deuotion in the actors, and hearers, and is alſo ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable in her Sacraments, eſpeciallie ſo eaſing, and acquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſoules in the Sacrament of Penance, as no teſtimonie, or demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtration vnder heauen, is, or can be, of like feeling proofe for the real goodnes and veritie of that Sacrament, as is the ſupernaturall, ſweeteſt, and diuine conſolation taſted therein, and in the Sacrament of the Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>25. A Religion whoſe ſecular and religious Cleargie liue without wiues, free from care of prouiding for children, and the later ſort no way diſtracted with the affaires and encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of the world, but encloiſtered, paſſe their whole time in prayer, watching, faſtin, in continuall ſtudie of ſcriptures, and in daily exerciſe and diſpute for full and perfect vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them: Helps that do moſt further the attaining of truth, and ſuch as are not found in the aduerſe partie, and which in common reaſon (Catholick Diuines being not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to other Diuines in wit, or other talents) ſhew, that our teachers (God being no acceptor of perſons) are more likely to haue (vſing fitter meanes for the ſame) the true intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and vnderſtanding of ſcripture, then are our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or contradictors.</p>
            <p>26. A religion of which the foure acknowledged Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of holie Church were both profeſſors, and ſtout defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as their owne works moſt apparantlie beare witneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> liuing 64. yeeres, and dying in the yeare of our Lord 397. purpoſely and approuinglie wrote of <note n="a" place="margin">Tom. 4. li. 2. de Sacramenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ca. 1. &amp; 2. &amp; lib. 3. cap. 1.</note> exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmes vſed before baptiſme, of <note n="b" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> vnction in baptiſme, of the perpetuall <note n="c" place="margin">Tom. 5. de vocatione gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li. 3. ca. 8. per totum.</note> alienation of infants from the ſight of God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8085:12"/> dying without baptiſme, of <note n="a" place="margin">Tom. 4. lib. 1. de poenitentia ca. 2. &amp; 6.</note> remiſſion of ſinne by a Prieſt, and who, as <hi>S. Paulinus</hi> recordeth in his life, heard auricular confeſſions, and ſo wept in hearing that he cauſed teares alſo in the penitents. He likewiſe wrote of the <note n="b" place="margin">Tom. 4. lib 4. de Sacramentis.</note> real preſence in the Sacrament of the altar, and of <note n="c" place="margin">Tom. 4. de Spirit. Sancto lib. 3. ca. 12.</note> adoration thereunto to be done, he obſerued, and commended the Lent-faſt <note n="d" place="margin">Tom. 1. Serm. de ieiunio Eliae.</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it the precept of Chriſt our Lord. In like manner hee wrote of <note n="e" place="margin">Tom 3. ſuper Apocal. ca. 14. &amp; 20.</note> Purgatorie, of <note n="f" place="margin">Lib. 5. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramen. cap. 1.</note> mingling water with wine in the chalice, he vſuallie ſaid Maſſe, wept bitterlie in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the dreadfull myſteries, and made <note n="g" place="margin">Tom. 5. in 1. precatione ad Miſſam praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante, &amp; epiſt. li. 5. epiſt. 33. ad Marcellinam ſororem ſuam.</note> prayers to be ſaid by Prieſts before Maſſe for duer preparation thereunto. Therefore vndoubtedly neither Proteſtant nor Puritane, but a Catholick Biſhop.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Hierome</hi> liuing 91. yeeres, and dying the yeere of our Lord 420. wrote <note n="h" place="margin">Tom. 2.</note> two bookes againſt the Apoſtata Monke <hi>Iouinian,</hi> and <note n="i" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> two other treatiſes againſt the lapſed Prieſt <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> in confutation of their ſtrange, and exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant points of doctrine: Namely, that marriage was of equall merit with widdowhead, or virginitie: That all meates might be eaten vpon all dayes, notwithſtanding any eccleſiaſticall ſanction to the contrary: That faſting had no reward with God: That there was no diſparitie of merits in this life, nor difference of glory in the next: That thoſe who with a full and entire faith had receiued grace in baptiſme, could not after leeſe the ſame. The poſitions of <hi>Iouinian.</hi> The phanſies of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantius</hi> theſe. The ſingle life, or vnmarried ſtate of Prieſts is opprobrious, Saincts were not to be worſhipped, nor prayed vnto, nor their reliques to be reuerenced, and the tapers or waxe-lights about their toombs were the enſignes of idolatrie, the retention of worldly ſubſtance better then voluntarie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, and the ſolitarines of Monks a thing vituperable.</p>
            <p>Againſt all which aſſertions, <hi>S. Hierome</hi> directlie, and of ſet purpoſe wrote, and wrote in ſome choler and anger, adding for reaſon, or excuſe, <hi>fatebor</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Aduerſus Vigilantium ad Riparium epiſt. 53.</note> 
               <hi>dolorem meum, ſacrilegium tantum patienter audire non poſſum,</hi> I will confeſſe my griefe, I am vnable patientlie to heare ſo great ſacrilege. Therefore
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8085:12"/> vndoubtedly neither Proteſtant nor Puritane, but a <note n="a" place="margin">Marianus Victorius epiſco. Reatinus in vita B. Hieronym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Et ipſe Hierony. Tom. 3. epiſt. 150. ad Hedibiam queſt. 2.</note> Maſſing Prieſt, Hermit, a great Pilgrimage <note n="b" place="margin">Ipſe Hierony. in Ezechi. ca. 4. &amp; in Apologia aduerſus Ruffinum, &amp; in plurim. ipſius epiſt. 8. 22. 43. &amp; alijs.</note> goer, a viſiter of holie places, and reliques.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Augustine</hi> liuing 76. yeeres, and dying the yeere of our Lord 430. wrote a <note n="c" place="margin">Tom. 4. ca. 18.</note> booke <hi>De cura pro mortuis gerenda,</hi> Of care to be had for the dead by the ſacrifices of the altar, prayer, and almes. Three <note n="d" place="margin">Tom. 1.</note> bookes <hi>De libero arbitrio,</hi> in the proofe of free will, a <note n="e" place="margin">Tom. 3.</note> booke <hi>De operis Monachorum,</hi> of the labour of Monks, wherein he approueth their ſtate, and conſequenthe alſo the vowes of pouertie, chaſtitie, and obedience: A <note n="f" place="margin">Tom. 4. maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè ca. 14. lib. eiuſdem.</note> booke <hi>De fide, &amp; operibus,</hi> of faith, and works, prouing abundantlie in it, as the principall ſcope, and end intended, that a ſole faith without good works is not ſufficient to ſaluation: He <note n="g" place="margin">Tom. 10 Serm. de tempore 255. qui eſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus de anniuerſario dedicationis eccleſia, vel al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taris. Et concil. Hippon. can. 6. cui interfuit S. Augustinus vt constat ex lib. 1. Retracta. ca. 17. &amp; Serm. 19. de Sanctis.</note> alloweth, and celebrated the conſecration of aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and the annointing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſm. Alſo he maketh mention, and requireth that the ſigne of the croſſe ſhould be made in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads of the beleeuers, and on the water, and Chriſm, with which they are regenerated, &amp; annointed. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he himſelfe moſt ſubmiſſiuely, and earneſtly inuocated <note n="h" place="margin">Tom. 9. li. meditationum ca. 40. &amp; Tom. 9. Serm. de Sanctis, Serm. 18.</note> the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed virgin <hi>Mary, S. Michael, S. Gabriel, S. Raphael,</hi> the Quiers of Angels, Archangels, Patriarks, Prophets, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Euangeliſts, Martyrs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, Prieſts; Leuits, Monks, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and of all the iuſt. In briefe, he <note n="i" place="margin">Tom. 6. de adulterinis coniugijs. lib. 1. ca. 8. &amp; 9. &amp; lib. 2. cap. 5.</note> reſolutely affirmeth, that after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce, neither the partie delinquent, nor innocent can marry againe, the other liuing, without committing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8085:13"/> the crime of adulterie, and in like manner agnizeth and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth the veritie of the fiue Sacraments, denyed, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named baſtard Sacraments by the aduerſarie, to wit, the <note n="a" place="margin">Tom. 2. lib. 2. contra lit. Petiliani ca. 104. &amp; Tom. 9. in epiſt. Iohan. tract. 3. &amp; 6.</note> Sacrament of Confirmation, <note n="b" place="margin">Tom. 10. Serm. de tempo 215. &amp; Tom. 9. li. 2. de viſitandis infirmis ca. 4. Item in tract. de rectitudine Catholicae conuerſati. ſi duo posteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores ſint Augustini.</note> Extreme vnction, <note n="c" place="margin">Tom. 7. contra epiſcop. Parm. li. 2. ca. 13. &amp; de baptiſ. contra Donatiſt. lib. 1. ca. 1.</note> Order, <note n="d" place="margin">Tom. 4. de fide, &amp; operib. ca. 7. &amp; Tom. 6. de bono coniugali, ca. 18. &amp; 24. &amp; Tom. 7. lib. de nuptijs, &amp; concupiſ. ca. 10.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, and <note n="e" place="margin">Tom. 4. de vera, &amp; falſa paenitentia ca. 10. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. Tom. 6. de adulterin. coniugijs ca. 28. Tom. 10. li. 50. homiliar. hom. 41. &amp; hom. 49. ca. 3. &amp; Tom. 8. in Pſalmum 63. circa medium.</note> Penance. He <note n="f" place="margin">Tom. 10. li. de tempore Serm. 251.</note> alſo ſharplie rebuketh thoſe that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglected to heare Maſſe, or did not ſtay in the Church ſo long as to the end of Maſſe, or ſhewed them-ſelues ſo colde and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in Gods ſeruice as to ſpeake to the Prieſt to abbreuiate, or be ſhort in his Maſſe. Therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlie neither Proteſtant, nor Puritane, but a <note n="g" place="margin">Poſſidius in vita eius.</note> Monke, inſtitutor of Monks, and ſtrongeſt maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our Catholike doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Gregory</hi> was firſt a <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. Diaconus in vita eius. lib. 1. ca. 6. 25. &amp; 39.</note> Monke, then choſen Abbot, then created Cardinall, and afterward elected Pope of Rome. In which dignitie he liued 13. yeeres, and odd moneths, and died the yeere of our Lord 604. He wrote in the allowance of <note n="i" place="margin">Lib. epiſt. 7. ca. 35.</note> Images, approued the making of <note n="k" place="margin">Eod. lib. cap. 109.</note> pictures in the walls and windowes of the Church, terming them the inſtruction, or bookes of the vnlearned, and reprehended the <note n="l" place="margin">Ibid. &amp; lib. epiſt. 9. ca. 9.</note> brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or defacing of them (only vpon abuſe which ſome ideots committed) as a thing not lawfull, and ſcandalous. He appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Monke <note n="m" place="margin">Tom. 1. li. 4. dialogorum. ca. 55.</note> 
               <hi>Precioſus</hi> to ſay Maſſe 30. dayes together for <hi>Iustus</hi> his fellow Monke deceaſed. Hee relateth <note n="n" place="margin">Ibid. ca. 57.</note> two miracles which God, through the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, moſt admirablie wrought. One, vpon a Captiue, whoſe fetters ſo often fell off, as his wife beleeuing him to be dead, procured Maſſe to be ſaid for his ſoule. The other vpon a Shipman named <hi>Baracha,</hi> who through the ſame moſt ſacred and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious oblation was, being reputed to be drowned, very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſlie fed, and deliuered after ſhipwrack. Hee augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8085:13"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Platina, &amp; Iohannes ſtella in vita eius.</note> the Letanie, ordained the <note n="b" place="margin">Iohannes Diaconus li. 2. ca. 18.</note> ſtations at Rome, incited to the going <note n="c" place="margin">Ipſe B. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorius li. 2. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ca. 21.</note> on pilgrimage, and viſitation of holy places. Hee greatly <note n="d" place="margin">Idem ibid. cap. 42.</note> affected to ſee, and reuerence the coate of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> Euangeliſt, and truſted to receiue ſpirituall profit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. He <note n="e" place="margin">Lib. 7. epiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum ca. 126.</note> ſent a piece of the Holy Croſſe, <note n="f" place="margin">Lib. 1. epiſt. ca. 29. &amp; 30. &amp; li. 6. epistol. cap. 189. &amp; lib. 11. epiſt. ca. 67.</note> Powder filed off from <hi>S. Peter</hi> and <hi>S. Paules</hi> chaines, ſome of <note n="g" place="margin">Lib. 7. epiſt. ca. 126.</note> 
               <hi>S. Iohn Baptists</hi> haire, and the <note n="h" place="margin">Lib. 5. epiſt. ca. 150.</note> reliques of other Martyrs, to ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall great perſonages for benediction, and veneration ſake. He trauailing in the gowt, and enforced oft to keepe his bed for his greater eaſe, roſe <note n="i" place="margin">Lib. 8. epiſt. cap 35.</note> notwithſtanding to ſay Maſſe vpon feſtiuall dayes, as himſelfe wrote of himſelfe to <hi>Eulogius</hi> the Patriarck of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and alſo approuinglie witneſſeth that <note n="k" place="margin">Lib. 7. epiſt. cap. 29.</note> Maſſe was daily ſaid at <hi>Rome</hi> in veneration of Saints. He wrote a letter to <hi>Melitus</hi> to tell <hi>S. Augustine</hi> our Apoſtle then conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> that he ſhould not deſtroy the temples of the idols in our countrie, but breake the idols, and ſprinckle <note n="l" place="margin">Lib. 9. epiſt. cap. 71. &amp; Beda de gestis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum lib. 1. cap. 30.</note> holy water about the ſame temples, build aultars, and put reliques in them. Therefore vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie neither Proteſtant, nor Puritane, but a Monke, and Pope, and zelous propagatour, and patron of Catholick religion.</p>
            <p>To ſay, that the aſſertions and points precedent were <hi>Naui patrum,</hi> the moales or blemiſhes, that ſhewed them to be men ſubiect to errour, and not to haue ſeene all things, were in our iudgement idleneſſe inough, and greateſt repugnancie; for let them be holden for Saintes, or ſaued ſoules (which we thinke no man of modeſtie, or yet of Chriſtianitie, will deny) it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth directly to bee impoſſible (wee meane if they dyed in the vnretracted faith they profeſſed in their bookes, as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to none of thoſe who are moſt againſt our religion, euer durſt to make open doubt thereof) that the foreſaid poſitions, and poyntes can be falſe, becauſe if they ſhould be falſe, and they containe, as then they ſhould doe, very damnable ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and higheſt idolatrie, (as approuing vayne doctrine, vaine reuerence, vaine ſacraments, vaine and impious rites, and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of bread in ſtead of God, (then which, nothing is more abhominable or idolatrous) it can not bee, moſt aſſuredly it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8085:14"/> cannot be, euen by the principles of our common Chriſtian faith, that the foreſaid doctors bee Saintes in heauen, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, moſt accurſed reprobates in hell, vnderſtanding as is before rehearſed, that they dyed in the beliefe they mainteyned in their writings.</p>
            <p>Againe, to ſay, they vnderſtood not the Scriptures, as well as doeth the beſt learned Proteſtant, or Puritane, and that through ſuch faile, and lacke of heauenly guidance, they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittingly ſlided into their errours, were to imagine <hi>Chimaeras,</hi> or ſome thing that were more ſtrange, and monſtrous: for what helpe enioyeth the Proteſtant, or Puritane, that they enioyed not? and they had many which the other haue not. They were a thouſand yeeres, and more, neerer vnto Chriſt, his Apoſtles, and their Diſciples, then the eldeſt Proteſtant, or Puritane, that can truely be named, and conſequently as like, if not more like, to heare, retriue, and learne the trueth, then any of the other two Profeſſions. They made Comments vpon all, or the moſt difficult partes of holy Scripture, they beat out the way, and vnſealed the hard, and hidden myſteries thereof, they layde the ground-workes of ſchoole diuinitie, brake the yee, and reconciled all the differing paſſages, which in the letter ſeemed to impugne, or contradict one the other.</p>
            <p>Or muſt it be conceyued, that theſe holy men working, and thorow-piercing into the ſelfe bowels, and abſtruſeſt depth of all diuinitie, and that very excellently, by the graunt of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries themſelues, could ſo maynely and contradictorily erre in matters of leſſe difficultie, as are the pointes controuerted? No, no, it cannot iuſtly be ſo conceiued, but rather, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite prouidence and goodneſſe of almightie God, becauſe he would not haue ſo ſacriligious a conceit harboured againſt the principall Doctors of the Church, hath in euery of their liues and deaths miraculouſly atteſted the contrary, if ſo much credit at leaſt may be giuen to the written liues of Saints, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by venerable perſonages, and receyued by many ages, as there is giuen to the relation of <hi>Plutarchs</hi> liues, or <hi>Caeſars</hi> Commentaries.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:8085:14"/>
            <p>S. <note n="a" place="margin">In vita S. Ambroſij.</note> 
               <hi>Paulinus</hi> reporteth that S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> being on a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne time in Rome, was inuited by a noble woman there, to come, and ſay Maſſe in her houſe, who yeelding to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, an other woman ſicke of the palſey vnderſtanding thereof, cauſed anon herſelfe to be brought in a chaire, into the roome where S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was, and kiſſing his garments, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently therewith recouered her health, and the perfect vſe of her limbes. Againe the ſame <note n="b" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> author recordeth, that <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> wife to <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperour, byring a murtherer to kil S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> for the exceeding hatred ſhe bore vnto him, who comming into his chamber, and lifting vp his arme with his ſworde drawne, to giue him his death, incontinent, his arme waxed ſo ſtiffe, and benummed, that he could neither ſtrike therewith, nor moue the ſame, but in confeſſing (which was no leſſe miraculous) who employed him in ſo outragious a fact, the vſe of his arme preſently returned, and he became as nimble therein as euer before. Other proofes of Gods ſpecial loue towards this ſaint, might be alledged, as <note n="c" place="margin">Ex Paulin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; 2. hist. Eccle. Ruffini libro. ca. 11. &amp; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uero Sulpitio in vita B. Marti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> his miraculous election to the Biſhopricke of Millan, his long extaſie, with which he was taken at the altar, when S. <hi>Martin</hi> Biſhop of Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron dyed; his prediction of the day of his death, before hee fell ſicke: the three viſions or admoniſhments, giuen by the voyce of God himſelfe, to <hi>Honoratus</hi> biſhop of Vercella, for his repaire to the ſaid ſaint, when he lay a dying, and for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring vnto him his laſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iaticum,</hi> the body of our Lorde: Theſe, wee ſay, might be alleadged for teſtimony of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Neuertheleſſe wee will content our ſelues with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall onely of that miracle which <note n="d" place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Paulinus</hi> mentioneth of an obſtinate Arian, who being preſent at a ſermon of ſaint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> ſawe (and was thereupon conuerted) an Angell to ſtand at his eare, whilſt he was preaching, &amp; appeared to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vnto him the words he ſpake to the people. All which are euident arguments of the ſaints true faith, his peculiar fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor with God, and of the vndoubted veritie of his doctrine.</p>
            <p>Touching S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> although both the ioynt cenſure of the <note n="a" place="margin">Sub Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centio 1 anno Christi 402.</note> Mileuitane Councel, conſiſting of 59. Biſhops, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8085:15"/> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was one, giuing him the attribute [Holie] in his life time, and the <note n="b" place="margin">In decreto de apocryphis Scripturis circi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter annum Christi 1495.</note> teſtification of S. <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> and of 70 other Biſhops in ſeſſion with him, ſurnaming him bleſſed, and moſt bleſſed after his death, bee argument ſufficient to proue his ſound faith and holineſſe; as alſo that our Sauiour moſt comfortably appeared vnto him in the houre of his death, as <hi>Marianus Victorius,</hi> and other writers of his life, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme: Yet becauſe we deſire to be more full in this point, wee thinke it neceſſary, hauing choiſe of miracles, to recite a fewe of many. S. <hi>Hierom</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Euſebius Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monenſis diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus B. Hieron. in epist de mort eius, ad Damaſum Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuenſem epiſcop. Habetur in cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Tom. 9. &amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur eſſe eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, teste Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura Reatim e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi Amerini in eundem Temum.</note> drawing neere to his ende, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſacrament of the Altar was brought vnto him, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued, and holding his armes acroſſe ouer his breaſt, ſayd the Hymne of holy <hi>Simeon,</hi> and preſently as that was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, there appeared ſo glorious a light in the roome where hee lay, as the exceeding brightneſſe, and ſplendor thereof pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and dazeling the beholders eyes, none that were preſent could any while endure to looke thereon; which continuing ſome ſpace, companies of Angels were ſeene, odoriferous ſmels felte, and a voyce heard, ſaying, <hi>Come my beloued, it is time that thou receyue thy reward for thy labours manfully ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in my cauſe.</hi> Being dead, the blind, deafe, dumb, &amp; ſick were <note n="d" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> healed, ſome by touching, ſome by kiſſing his body. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the poſſeſſed brought in preſence of the corps, the diuels going out of them, cryed, <note n="e" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Holy Hierome, why doeſt thou thus grieuouſly torment vs? thou wert alwayes our ſcourge, both liuing, and now dead.</hi> What neede more recitals? God ſeemed ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully tender, and zealous of his ſeruants fame, and honor, as <note n="f" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> when a certayne Heretike enraged with enuy, againſt the working of the foreſaid miracles, and wiſhing that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy were burnt; himſelfe was preſently by fire deſcending from heauen, conſumed to aſhes: whereupon many other infected with the ſame hereſie, were perfectly conuerted. Wonderful thinges! but they are ſaintes that reporte them, ſaintes that wrought them, and <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 67. verſ. 36.</note> 
               <hi>God is admirable in his Saintes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue beene long in the Narrations precedent, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our briefeneſſe in the two that follow muſt be the greater.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8085:15"/> 
               <hi>Poſſidius</hi> Biſhop, and diſciple of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who liued almoſt <note n="a" place="margin">Cap. vlt. de vita Auguſtin.</note> fortie yeeres familiarly with him, as himſelfe writeth, affirms <note n="b" place="margin">Cap. 29. ibid.</note> that he knew S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> both when he was Prieſt, &amp; after he was Biſhop, to haue (being abſent) expelled diuels from out the poſſeſſed, by meanes of his prayers, and teares for them: And that in his death-bed, hee <note n="c" place="margin">Cap. eodem.</note> cured a ſicke-man, by laying his handes vpon him, whome God by viſion had commanded to repaire to that ende vnto him. By which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle his diuine goodneſſe intended no doubt, as it were with his owne hand, and ſeale, to teſtifie to the world, and all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, the holineſſe of his ſeruant, and the trueth, and pietie of the doctrine he had taught.</p>
            <p>Concerning S. <hi>Gregorie,</hi> his <note n="d" place="margin">Iohanne. Diaconus lib. 2. cap. 22. de vita B. Greg.</note> receiuing of an Angell, and of <note n="e" place="margin">Ibid. cap. 23.</note> the Lord of Angels in the perſons of poore Pilgrimes to his table, is ſufficient proofe of his ſanctitie, and of Gods extraordinary loue towards him. And that he taught no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, ſuperſtitious, or falſe doctrine, it is likewiſe manifeſt, by the ſitting of the holy Ghoſt on his head, in forme of a Doue, at the time of writing his boobes, as <note n="f" place="margin">Apud Iohan. Diac. lib. 4. cap. 69. de vita B. Gregorij.</note> 
               <hi>Petrus Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> a deare familiar friend of S. <hi>Gregories,</hi> and much conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with him, witneſſeth to haue ſeen moſt often. How pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable alſo this holy Doctors prayers were with God, it well appeareth by this, that for the <note n="g" place="margin">Idem lib. 2. cap. 41.</note> conuerſion of an incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and misbeleeuing woman, thinking the bread which her ſelfe had made, could not be chang'd into the body of Chriſt, he both turned a ſacred hoſt into appearance of fleſh, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againe into the forme of bread, as it carried before. Which with other manifold miracles of his, moſt clearely teſtifieth, that he was neither of ill life, nor ill beliefe, but holy in the one, and Apoſtolicall in the other.</p>
            <p>Neither did the ſaid foure Doctors (a conſideration of much importance) differentlie teach, or one impugne the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any of the points of doctrine aboue mentioned, but they all concurred in one vniformitie of opinion without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, or leaſt ſhew of diſſent. Yea not only theſe foure moſt renowned Clearks, the chiefe lights of Gods Church
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8085:16"/> next after the Apoſtles, agreed moſt vniformelie, as we haue ſaid, in the foreſaid controuerted points of religion, but all the primitiue writers conſpired likewiſe in the ſame. As in proofe of the ſacrifice, vſe, and holineſſe of the Maſſe. <note n="a" place="margin">Apostolicar. constitut. li. 6. ca. 23. &amp; epiſt. 2. &amp; 3. de officio ſacerdotum, &amp; clericor.</note> 
               <hi>Clement</hi> conſecrated <note n="b" place="margin">Tertullian. de praeſcript. cap 32. Epiphanius haereſi. 27. Ruffinus in praefati libri Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>S. Peter.</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſiasti. Hierar. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius Areopagita S. Pauls</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 15.</note> diſciple, and by him <note n="e" place="margin">Heldumus Abbas.</note> ordained Biſhop of <hi>Athens:</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Epiſt. ad Smyrn.</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius S. Iohn</hi> Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts <note n="g" place="margin">Simeon Metaphrastes in vita eius.</note> auditor, and by common co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Apoſtles aſſigned Biſhop of <hi>Antioch.</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Aduerſus haereſ. lib. 4 ca 32. &amp; 34 &amp; lib. 5. ca. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſcholar <note n="i" place="margin">Feu-ardentius in vita eius.</note> to <hi>S. Policarp,</hi> and he ſcholar to <hi>S. Iohn:</hi> Pope <note n="k" place="margin">Epiſt. 1. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Anacletus</hi> the fourth from <hi>S. Peter:</hi> Pope <note n="l" place="margin">Epiſt. 1. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond from <hi>Anacletus:</hi> Pope <note n="m" place="margin">Epiſt. ad omnes vniuerſaliter cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rus</hi> the ſecond fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> with others their next ſucceſſors, <note n="n" place="margin">Apud Gratianum de conſecratione distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione 1. cano. omnes Baſilicae.</note> 
               <hi>Higinus,</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">In Codice 5. librorum li. 4. ca. 117.</note> 
               <hi>Pius,</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Apud Burchardum lib. 5. ca. 29. &amp; Iuonem part. 2. cap. 98.</note> 
               <hi>Anicetus,</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Apud Gratianum de conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crati. diſt. 1. cano. hoc quoque.</note> 
               <hi>Soter,</hi> all receiued Saincts, and Martyrs. Alſo the Liturgie of the church of <hi>Rome</hi> deliuered by <hi>S. Peter,</hi> the Liturgie of the church of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> written by <hi>S. Iames,</hi> the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> compoſed by <hi>S. Marke,</hi> the Liturgie of the church of <hi>Milan</hi> made by <hi>S. Barnabas.</hi> The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie of the church of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> compiled by <note n="r" place="margin">Ploruit circi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter annum. 370.</note> 
               <hi>S. Baſil.</hi> The Liturgie of the church of <hi>Constantinople</hi> ſet forth by <hi>S.</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Floruit anno Christi. 380.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſostome:</hi> And likewiſe the Liturgies of the <hi>Aethiopian, Syrian,</hi> and <hi>Armenian</hi> churches, which all with ſome other do moſt cleerely witneſſe the ſacrifice, vſe, and veneration of the Maſſe, and do alſo approue the ceremonies, and diuine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries repreſented, and expreſſed therein.</p>
            <p>In like manner for proofe, and direct euidence of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent practiſe, fruite and obligation of auricular Confeſſion,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8085:16"/> 
               <hi>S.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Apostolicar. constitut. lib. 2. cap. 33. &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 1. ad Iacobum fratrem Domini.</note> 
               <hi>Clement, S.</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Epiſt. 8. ad Demophilum.</note> 
               <hi>Dionyſius, S.</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Aduerſus haereſes lib. 1. ca. 9. floruit circi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an. 160.</note> 
               <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Homil. 2. in Leuiticum. &amp; Hom. in Pſal. 37. floruit 230.</note> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Lib. de paenitentia cap. 10. &amp; 12 floruit 200.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian, S.</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Lib. de lapſis floruit 250.</note> 
               <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Li. 4 diuinar. conſtitution. ca. 17. floruit 320.</note> 
               <hi>Lactantius,</hi> who ſo highly aduanceth Confeſſion, as he maketh it one diſtinctiue note <note n="h" place="margin">Idem cap. vlt. eiuſdem libri.</note> of the true Church, <hi>S.</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Serm. in illa verba Profecti in pagum qui cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aduerſ. &amp;c. floruit circiter annum 340.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius, S.</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Canone 18. in Matthaeum flor. 346.</note> 
               <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larie,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Lib. de paenitentia, &amp; confeſſ. flor. 350.</note> 
               <hi>Pacianus, S.</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">In regulis breui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rib. regula 229. &amp; 288.</note> 
               <hi>Baſil, S.</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Tom. 5. lib. 2. de ſacerdotio.</note> 
               <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostom, S.</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Epiſt. 80. ad epiſcopos Campaniae, &amp; epiſt 91. ad Theodorum Foroiulij epiſcopum flor. 450.</note> 
               <hi>Leo,</hi> with other writers of beſt note in euery age ſince Chriſtes time hitherto. And as the primitiue and ancient Fathers and Saincts do yeeld their abundant teſtimonie in confirmation of theſe two points, ſo do they vndoubtedlie alſo afford, if this place would giue leaue, to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularize, very ample euidence in all the other points before mentioned, and in queſtion betweene vs and our oppoſitors. Nay, if we may be ſo bold as to deliuer our opinion plainely without concealing ought in this matter: the maner that our aduerſaries vſe in citing places out of the auncient Fathers againſt vs, is but the ſtudie of meere wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and no other then a demonſtratiue token of an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding contentious ſpirit, wilfullie affecting to blindfold and miſlead it ſelfe. For were they ſincere and loued truth aboue all things, they could not poſſible diſmember, wreſt and pick out ſentences of their works, in the order and to the purpoſes they do, not letting to rack their words to a ſenſe which the writers neuer meant: yea contrarie oftentimes euen to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſcope and drift of thoſe bookes whence they cull the peeces they alleadge, contrarie to the euident letter and plaine paſſages of their other writings, contrarie to the faith they profeſſed, liued and died in; contrarie to the religion of the age they wrote in; contrarie to the doctrine of the Church that firſt admitted them for Doctors, or receiued them for Saincts; contrarie to the profeſſion of their liues and ſtate of vocation; contrarie to the language and nature of their owne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8085:17"/> deedes; to the titles and dignities they held, and to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and cenſure which all former ages retained of ſuch their parcels of writing. So that words, and words commonly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynted from that went before, or followeth after, muſt bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and beare more ſway and credit for condemning vs of error, then the writers liues, ſelfe deedes, their practiſe, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, other their works, or neuer ſo many apparant teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of theirs to the contrarie for the truth of our religion.</p>
            <p>27. A religion, of whoſe doctrine and communion in Sacraments all the Saincts in the Kalendar, the patrons of Churches &amp; countries, conuerters of nations to Chriſtianitie, all perſonages of either ſexe memorable for holines, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the world, for mortifying their appetites, for ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendring their wills, or for any other excellent, and true virtue, were, and ſo liued, and died, as the authenticall legends of their liues, and other eccleſiaſticall writings do teſtifie, and beare apparent record to the whole world.</p>
            <p>28. A religion not deſtitute of any kinde of proofe; but her poſitions confirmable by Scriptures, by Apoſtolicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, by Counſels oecumenicall, and prouinciall, by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Doctors, reaſon, hiſtories, chronologies, propheſies, viſions, reuelations, miracles, traditions, and by all theſe, and other like heads, we ſay, confirmable, without wreſt, ſtraine, or flying to tropes, or figuratiue ſpeeches. So as theſe words in the Canticles ſeeme only verifide of our church, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>Thy neck</hi> (that is the puiſſance of Chriſtes Church) <hi>is as</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cantic. 4. v. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the towre of Dauid, which is built with bulwarks, a thouſand ſhields hang on it, all the armour of the ſtrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>29. A religion, which <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 2.</note> beginning at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> hath as a riuer through the length of her courſe euer more and more increaſed, and ſpread it ſelfe, as it was propheſied that the Church of Chriſt ſhould, <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>I will giue thee</hi> (ſaith God the Father to God the Sonne) <hi>nations to thine inheritance</hi> (which is his Church) <hi>and the ends of the earth to thy poſſeſsion:</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eſay. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>All nations ſhall run vnto her.</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 7. 14.</note> 
               <hi>All people, tribes, and tongs ſhall ſerue him.</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Eſay. 60. 10.</note> 
               <hi>The ſonnes of ſtrangers</hi> (that is of the Gentils)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8085:17"/> 
               <hi>ſhall build vp her walls, and their Kings do ſeruice vnto her.</hi> Now that theſe, and innumerable other like predictions and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies are only found true, and fulfilled in our Catholick Roman church and religion, both the ſeuerall conuerſions of nations vnto her, and the infinite multitude diſperſed euery-where of her beleeuers, do, as nothing can more, clearely teſtifie: And how greatly it ſpred it ſelfe, euen when it firſt put forth after the death of our Sauior, it appeares by the ſeuerall people &amp; nations to whom <hi>S. Paul</hi> directed particular Epiſtles, namely, the <hi>Romans, Corinthians, Galatians, Epheſians, Philippians, Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Theſſalonians, Hebrews,</hi> by miſſion of the Apoſtles into all quarters of the world to preach the ſame, by <hi>S. Peters</hi> writing to the Iewes diſperſed in <hi>Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Bithynia,</hi> by the contents of the 2. and 4. Chapters of the Acts of the Apoſtles, where the conuerſion of 8000. is ſpecified through two Sermons preached by <hi>S. Peter.</hi> Likewiſe what ample, and moſt meruailous increaſe it tooke afterward in the ſecond age, <note n="a" place="margin">In dialogo cum Tryph.</note> 
               <hi>Iustinus Philoſophus,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Ireneus,</hi> and <note n="c" place="margin">In Apolog. cap. 37. &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Iudaeos ca. 7. &amp; 8.</note> 
               <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> do witneſſe. And ſo doth <note n="d" place="margin">De vit. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſoph. in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſio.</note> 
               <hi>Eunapius Sardianus</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane writer, and enimie of Chriſtian religion, <note n="e" place="margin">Vit. Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tini li. 3. ca. 24. &amp; ſequ. &amp; cae. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Lib. 1. ca. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Socrates</hi> with others for the third age.</p>
            <p>And touching the ſucceeding Centuries, to the end it may appeare how our Catholike religion did in euery age ſpread and dilate it ſelfe according to the former prophecies, we will recite a fewe of many Nations that were conuerted in euery Countrey to the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the fourth age were conuerted the <hi>Beſſites, Dacians, Getes,</hi> and <hi>Scythians</hi> by <note n="g" place="margin">S. Paulinus de reditu Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetae in Dac.</note> 
               <hi>S. Nicetas</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dacia</hi> to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Romane faith. The <hi>Morins,</hi> and <hi>Neruians</hi> by <note n="h" place="margin">S. Paulinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> epiſt. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Victricius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Roan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And within the compaſſe of this centurie <note n="i" place="margin">Epiſt. 3.</note> 
               <hi>S. Hierome</hi> alſo writeth that other Nations were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as the <hi>Armenians</hi> and <hi>Huns,</hi> adding <note n="k" place="margin">Idem epiſt. 7.</note> that troupes of Monks came daily from <hi>India, Perſia,</hi> and <hi>Aethiopia</hi> vnto him.</p>
            <p>In the fifth age the Saracens by <note n="l" place="margin">Cyrillus in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta S. Euthymij apud Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrasten die 20. Ianu.</note> 
               <hi>S. Euthymius</hi> Monke, and <hi>Aſpebetus.</hi> The <note n="m" place="margin">Socrates lib. 7. ca. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Burgundians</hi> vpon this motiue of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods eſpeciall and moſt ſingular fauours and protection
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8085:18"/> towards the Romane Chriſtian Monarchie in times of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe. The <note n="a" place="margin">Proſper aduerſus collatorem in fine.</note> Scots by <hi>Palladius,</hi> ſent <note n="b" place="margin">A. D. 429.</note> by Pope <hi>Caeleſtine,</hi> the French <note n="c" place="margin">Gregor. Turon. de gest is Franc. li. 2. ca. 31.</note> by <hi>S. Remigius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Reims,</hi> and <note n="d" place="margin">Albin. Flac. circiter A. D. 499.</note> 
               <hi>S. Vedastus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arras.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſixth age the <note n="e" place="margin">A. D. 565.</note> Northerne Picts by <note n="f" place="margin">Beda de geſt. Angl. li. 3. ca. 4.</note> 
               <hi>S. Columbus</hi> Abbot The <note n="g" place="margin">A. D. 589.</note> 
               <hi>Goths</hi> by <note n="h" place="margin">Gregor. Turonen. Hiſt. Fran. lib. 8. ca. 41.</note> 
               <hi>Leander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Seuil.</hi> The <note n="i" place="margin">A. D. 590.</note> 
               <hi>Bauarians</hi> by <note n="k" place="margin">A. D. 594.</note> 
               <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Worms.</hi> The <note n="l" place="margin">Gregor. epiſt. lib. 3. ca. 29. &amp; 27.</note> 
               <hi>Barbaricinians</hi> by <note n="m" place="margin">A. D. 596.</note> 
               <hi>Foelix</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, &amp; <hi>Cyriacus</hi> Abbot. The <note n="n" place="margin">Beda de geſt. Angl. lib. 1. ca. 23.</note> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh by <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> a Benedictine Monke, ſent by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>In the 7. age, the Flemings by <note n="o" place="margin">Iaco. Mayer in Chron. Flandriae. 649.</note> 
               <hi>Eligius:</hi> the <hi>Weſtphalians</hi> by the <note n="p" place="margin">Faſciculus temporum.</note> two <hi>Eualdes,</hi> after honored with the crowne of martirdome: multitudes of Spaniards by <note n="q" place="margin">Volaterranu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. 21. &amp; Vincentius lib. 23. ca. 92.</note> 
               <hi>S. Andonius,</hi> chiefly through the miracle he wrought in calling ſtore of raine from heauen by his prayers, when in ſeauen yeares before there had fallen none in that place: The people of <hi>Franconia</hi> by <note n="r" place="margin">Sigibertus in Chronico. 688.</note> 
               <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus</hi> ſent by Pope <hi>Cuno:</hi> and the Friſians by <note n="ſ" place="margin">Trithemius de Regib. Franc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um 696.</note> 
               <hi>S. Willibrode</hi> an Engliſhman, imployed in that holie worke by <hi>Pipin</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and Pope <hi>Sergius</hi> the firſt.</p>
            <p>In the eight age, the <note n="t" place="margin">Hedio lib. 6. ca. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Haſſuts,</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Chronic. Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacenſe.</note> 
               <hi>Thuringians</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mutius lib. 7. &amp; Hartmannus Schedel in Chro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tate 6.</note> 
               <hi>Erphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> and <note n="y" place="margin">Willibaldus in vita Bonifacij 722.</note> 
               <hi>Cattians</hi> by <hi>S. Boniface,</hi> an Engliſh Monke: the Lumbards by <hi>Sebaldus</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Hartmannus vbi ſupra.</note> ſent by Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſecond. The Iewes of the Citie of <hi>Berythum</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Crantzius in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>trop. lib. 1. ca. 9 &amp; Magd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. 8. tit. de Propagat. 785.</note> by the bleeding of a Crucifix, which the ſaid Iewes had contumeliouſlie ſtabbed, and the blood whereof cured all diſeaſes. The two Saxon Dukes <note n="*" place="margin">Witekindus ſawe this viſion at Wolmerstadium on the feaſt of Easter, when the Campe of Carolus magnus lay there.</note> 
               <hi>Witekindus</hi> and <hi>Albion,</hi> by a miraculous ſight which <hi>Witekindus</hi> ſawe whilſt he was but in a new and doubtfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of becomming Chriſtian, to wit, a faire childe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from the Prieſts hands into the mouthes of the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8085:18"/> when, celebrating Maſſe, he deliuered the ſacrament of the Altar to Communicants.</p>
            <p>In the ninth age, the <note n="a" place="margin">Adamus li. 1. ca. 16. &amp; 17. &amp; Grantzius in metrop. lib. 1. ca. 19. 826.</note> 
               <hi>Danes,</hi> and <hi>Suethens,</hi> by <hi>S. Ausgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> Monke: the <note n="b" place="margin">Blondus Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Deca. 2. li 2. 840</note> 
               <hi>Bulgarians</hi> by <hi>S. Ioannicius:</hi> the <note n="c" place="margin">Helmoldus li. 1. ca. 6. &amp; li. 2. ca. 12. in hiſt. Scla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Rugians</hi> by the Monks of <hi>Corbeia:</hi> the <note n="d" place="margin">Theodomarus Epiſcopus Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienſis ad Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annem Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficem.</note> 
               <hi>Morauians,</hi> by <hi>Withungum:</hi> the <note n="e" place="margin">Zonaras tom. 3. &amp; Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drenus. 875.</note> 
               <hi>Rhoſſits</hi> vpon euidence of the miracle enſuing. They demaunded of the Prieſt, whom their Emperour <hi>Baſilius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo</hi> ſent vnto them to teach them the Chriſtian Catholike faith, by what powerfull and diuine ſigne, he would witnes the truth of his doctrine. The ſigne was, that if the booke wherein the ſaid doctrine was written ſhould not burne being caſt into the fier, then they all with one accord would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently beleeue and receiue his doctrine. A great fier was made, and the Prieſt putting the booke (which was the holie Bible) into the middeſt thereof, ſaid with a lowd voyce, <hi>Glorifica no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tuum Christe Deus,</hi> Chriſt our God glorify thy holy name. The flames gaue place to the booke, and the booke lay ſo long in the fier as the people themſelues thought meete, and when it was taken out, it appeared ſound, whole, and no one leafe either ſcorched or blemiſhed.</p>
            <p>In the tenth age the Polonians by<note place="margin">f Adamus li. 2. ca. 7. 8. 10. 11. &amp; D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>maru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chron. lib. 2. 971.</note> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Cromerus, &amp; alij de reb. Polonorum. 965.</note> 
               <hi>Aegidius, Tuſculanks,</hi> and others ſent by Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13. The <hi>Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonians</hi> by <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>A. D.</hi> 989. h <hi>Cartuitius in vita St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ph. Hungar. reg. ca. 1. 2. &amp; 3. &amp; Aeneas Syl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Hiſt. Bohem. ca 16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Adelbert,</hi> and the <note n="h" place="margin">A. D. 1012. Helmoldus li. 2. ca. 13. &amp; Mar. Crom. lib. 7.</note> Hungarians by <note n="i" place="margin">Aeneas Syluius.</note> another <hi>Adelbert</hi> ſurnamed their Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>In the eleuenth age the <note n="k" place="margin">A. D. 1106. Bozius lib. 4. ca. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and multitudes of <hi>Pruſſians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the reclaiming of the lapſed <note n="l" place="margin">Circiter A. D. 1150. Ranulphus li. 7. ca. 22.</note> Hungarians.</p>
            <p>In the twelfth age, the Pomeranians, the Noruegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by <hi>Nicholas</hi> an Engliſh Moncke, employed in that holie worke, by Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the third: The which <hi>Nicholas</hi> was afterwarde choſen Pope of Rome, and named <hi>Hadrian</hi> the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8085:19"/> fourth, and gaue the dominion of Ireland to king <hi>Henrie</hi> 2.<note place="margin">Stow in anno 7. Henrici 2.</note> with condition of propagating the Chriſtian faith there; of preſeruing the rights of the Church entire, and inuiolated, and of paying a yeerely penſion of a penny for euery houſe in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>In the 13. age, the <note n="a" place="margin">Anno Dom. 1205.</note> Liuonians, by <note n="b" place="margin">Crantzius lib. 7. cap. 13.</note> 
               <hi>S. Medardes,</hi> the <note n="c" place="margin">An. Dom. 1230.</note> Lituanians by <note n="d" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtinus Chromer. lib. 8.</note> the knightes of S. <hi>Marie,</hi> the <note n="e" place="margin">Anno Dom. 1270. Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus, &amp; G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lmus de Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giaco.</note> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Caſſanes</hi> with innumerable Tartarians.</p>
            <p>In the four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teenth age, <note n="f" place="margin">Anno Dom. 1300 Niceph. Gregor. Histor. lib. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Azatines</hi> Emperour of the Turkes, the Iſles of the Canaries, the <note n="g" place="margin">Anno Dom. 1344. Bozius lib. 4. cap. 5.</note> reuolted Lituanians, the <note n="h" place="margin">Anno Dom. 1346. Sebaſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Munſterus in Coſmograph.</note> Cumans, the Boſnians, the Lipnenſians, the Patrini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and other Sclauonian nations, by Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 6. and <hi>Lewes</hi> king of Hungarie.</p>
            <p>In the fifteenth age, the <note n="i" place="margin">Anno Dom. 1350. Michael. Rit. lib. 2. Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin. deca. 2. lib. 10.</note> Samogetians the kingdomes of Bentonine, Guinea, Angola, and <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno Dom. 1412. Martin. Chrom. lib.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> Congo.</p>
            <p>In the ſixteenth and laſt age, to ſpeake in generall, without deſcending to any particulars, more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>inces, Nations, and numbers of rich Kingdomes, and Empires, were brought to the knowledge of Chriſt, and embracing the catholike Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane faith, by the labours of the Dominican and Franciſcan Friers, and the fathers of the ſocietie of Ieſus, God atteſting his cauſe and trueth by ſeuerall miracles, then all Chriſtendom twice, yea, perhaps more then thrice tolde, contayned before: which, beſide the record of all Coſmographies, and Hiſtories of this ſubiect, may plainely bee demonſtrated in that before the laſt Centenarie, or not many yeeres different, the Chriſtian Religion extended not it ſelfe beyond the riuer Ganges Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the Iſles of the Canaries in the Weſt, which ſcope and ſpace is counted no more then of an hundreth and twenty degrees; but the circuite of the world, which is now ſailed, and euery, or moſt where, portes of Chriſtians found therein, is of three hundred and threeſcore degrees, which is full out thrice<note place="margin">l <hi>Anno Dom. 1485.</hi>
               </note> as much.</p>
            <p>The fewe precedents (moſt renowmed Prince) collected out of many that might be added, doe very cleerely ſhew, not onely that the aboue-rehearſed, and other propheſies, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8085:19"/> of God of <hi>dilating the place of his Tents, and of ſpreading</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 54. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>out the curtaines of his Tabernacle,</hi> that is, the boundes of his Church, (Chriſts Spouſe and temporall Kingdome) are to the eye fulfilled, in the encreaſing ſocieties, and continuance of our religion, but that alſo the <hi>Word of wiſedome,</hi> and the <hi>Worde of knowledge</hi> (graces giuen by the teſtimonie of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the Church, by the holy Ghoſt, to the profite of others) haue their reſidences in the teachers of our religion, and that in how eminent and moſt powerfull manner, the conuerſion of the former Nations beareth moſt apparant witneſſe, for there can be no doubt made, but that ſome, if not the moſt parte of the foreſayde Nations and ſortes of people, were of excellent dexteritie and iudgement, and therefore very vnlike that they were ledde away, ſpecially from the religion and rites they were bredde and borne in, without ſtore of ſolide and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall reaſons mouing them thereunto. And it is as little que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, whether ſome of them were not alſo of a knotty; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable or vntameable nature, of a prowde, obſtimate and hawtie diſpoſition, drowned in vncleaneneſſe, and delighting in the varieties of libertie: lets and ſtrongeſt impeachments of imbracing the diſcipline, pureneſſe and auſteritie of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian catholike religion: and the conquering of them a plaine demonſtration that their Conuerters (all ſtoute profeſſors of the Romane religion) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aught that doctrine, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet calleth <hi>a lawe, conuerting ſoules:</hi> and the Apoſtle, <hi>the liuely</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 18. 8. Heb. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and forcible word, more piercing then any two edged ſword.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that they fought not with the leather ſheathe, the letter onely of Scripture, but with the letter and true ſenſe, which onely is the <hi>Sword of the ſpirit, that reacheth vnto the diuiſion of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 17. Heb 4 12. Luke 1. 79. Eſa. 30. 23.</note> 
               <hi>the ſoule. The bright Candle</hi> (Luke 11. 37.) <hi>that illuminateth thoſe that ſitte in darkeneſſe.</hi> And <hi>the ſeede to which God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to giue rayne for the rich fructifying thereof.</hi> And finally, that they were alſo true imitators of the Apoſtles in doctrine and office, as becomming <hi>Fiſhers of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> drawing them out of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Matth 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; Mark. 1. 17.</note> the Sea of infidelitie, into the harbour of Chriſtianitie, a badge or attribute giuen to the Apoſtles, and verified in none but in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8085:20"/> catholike teachers. Neither did then, nor doth now the <hi>word of wiſedom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and knowledge</hi> (a gifte proper to Gods Church)<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 8.</note> worke in our catholike teachers vpon Infidels onely, but the ſame extended and ſtill extendeth his power and diuine effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to the bringing forth of as rare or more rare effectes, vpon beleeuing Chriſtians, namely, in exciting men and women of all ages and eſtates, euen <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amba King of Spaine. Hugo King of Prouince. Rachis King of Lombardie. Sigiſmundus King of Burgundie. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>remundus King of Castile. Ranimirus King of Aragon. Ethelred, and K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neredus Kings of Mercia.
<table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sigebert.</cell>
                           <cell rows="4">Kings of Northumberland.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>A frod.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Ceolulphus.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Egbert.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>bba,</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">Kings of England.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Offa, and Ina.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table> Henry he fourth, King of Denmarke. Carlomannus King of Almaine. Trebellius King of Bulgarie. Cazimirus King of Poland, and others.</p>
               </note> Kings, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <p>Radegund Queene of France. Margaret Queene of France. Brigit Queene of Sueden. Etheldreda Queene of Northumbers.
<table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sexbarga.</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">Q. Q. of Weſtſaxons, &amp; others.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Ethelburga.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </note> Queenes. <note n="c" place="margin">Lotharius Earle of Romans, and others.</note> Emperours, <note n="d" place="margin">Richardix wife of Carolus Craſſus Emperour. Chunegundis wife of Henry Emper. and others.</note> and Empreſles to relinquiſh the world, renounce the pleaſures and delights thereof, and deuote and binde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to a poore, chaſt, and obedient life, vnder the command and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of others: Of which religious companies ſome eate no fleſh but in time of ſickneſſe only, or other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, and obſerue both ſilence, and ſolitarineſſe, as do the Benedictines; ſome neuer eate fleſh at all, weare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſhirts of haire, go not forth of their Cloyſters, nor ſpeake to their fellowes but with leaue, as doe the <hi>Carthuſians:</hi> ſome neither eate fleſh, egs, nor whit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-meates, and faſt three parts of the yere, as do the <hi>Bouhomes;</hi> Some diſcipline themſelues ſundrie times in the weeke, or daily go bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote, touch no money, haue nothing in proper nor in common, and beg their foode from dore to dore, as do the <hi>Capuccines:</hi> ſome attend the ſick in all diſeaſes, aſſiſt them with ghoſtly counſell, prouide them Sacraments, and burie their dead bodies as do certaine fraternities: ſome clenſe vlcers, and feſtered ſores, nor refuſe any office, how baſe and loathſome ſoeuer about impotent criples and lazars, as do the Nunnes of <hi>S. Elizabeths</hi> order: And all theſe, with other diuers orders, that after another manner labour to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8085:20"/> themſelues, and do good to others, he vpon no other beds but of ſtraw, riſe at midnight, ſleepe little, and ſpend much time in prayer, and meditation. Which are no conditions of life, that either <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13. 14</note> 
               <hi>make prouiſion for the fleſh in concupiſcences,</hi> or <note n="b" place="margin">Galat. 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>do ſeeke to accompliſh the deſires,</hi> or <note n="c" place="margin">Titus. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſerue the voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof</hi> (ſinnes which the Apoſtle forbiddeth) but rather formes of life that <note n="d" place="margin">Galat. 5. 24.</note> 
               <hi>crucifie the fleſh, with her vices, and concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences,</hi> do <note n="e" place="margin">Galat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 19.</note> 
               <hi>naile them to the Croſſe with Chriſt,</hi> and render both <note n="f" place="margin">Galat. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>the world crucifide to thoſe that ſo liue, and them to the world.</hi> Vertues which by the teſtimonie of the ſame Apoſtle <note n="g" place="margin">Galat. 5. 24.</note> 
               <hi>make their dooers the ſeruants of Chriſt,</hi> and <note n="h" place="margin">Galat. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>to liue now not they, but Chriſt in them.</hi> Effects of no falſe religion.</p>
            <p>30. A religion, from which Countries eyther departing. or mingling other doctrines with it, made preſent wracke of their former felicities, falling eyther into flatte Apoſtafie, or moſt lamentable bondage, or both. The inſtances are: The <note n="i" place="margin">Theodoretu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. 4. cap. 32. Sozomen. lib. 6. cap. 37.</note> Goths, while they remained Catholike, floriſhed and enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their territories, but becomming Arians, were ſhortly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thence by the Hunnes, then Infidels: The like, and by like occaſion befell the <note n="k" place="margin">Iornandes de rebus geſt.</note> Dacians, Myſians, and Pannoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by inuaſion of the Hunnes, Gepides and Rugians. The <note n="l" place="margin">Ex Aenea Silu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, in Eur. cap. 16. 17. Anto. Sabel. Enne 10. lib. 6. &amp; ex Chronicis earundem Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum, alijſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Historijs.</note> Dalmatians, Gaulls, Britanes, Spaniards, and the Africans by ſuperinducing or mixing, one the hereſie of <hi>Manichaes,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other the heriſie of <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> the thirde the hereſie of <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> the fourth the hereſie of <hi>Priſcillian,</hi> the laſt the hereſie of <hi>Donatus,</hi> with the catholike religion, were conquered, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, the Dalmatians by the Turke, the Gaules by the French, the Britaines by the Engliſh, the Spaniardes by the Goths, the Africanes by the Vandals: To which may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Germanes, waſted and ſubiected by <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tila</hi> to the ſeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory of the Hunnes after the Arian hereſie had rooted it ſelfe in ſeuerall quarters and prouinces of their Countrey: The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants alſo of the citie Iulinum, who being conuerted to the<note place="margin">Ortelius in Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia. ex Saxone Helmold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Cran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zio.</note> Romane faith, and falling againe from it were all conſumed, both cittizens and cittie with fire from heauen. Touching the Countries in the Eaſt, after they beganne to diſhonour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8085:21"/> with newe doctrines, they ſo faſt ratine headlong there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, (an inſeparable propertie of all hereſie, becauſe they are vnbounded, and lacke a defining and binding power) that in ſhort while after, to witte, in the raigne of <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, there were on foote <note n="d" place="margin">Nic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph. lib. 18. 45. Iacobitans. Georgians. Theopaſchite. Armeniaens. Monophyſites. Agnoetans. Staurablatans. Monothelites. Seuerites. Aphtarthodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites. Phantaſiasts. Manichaes. Tetradites. Tritheites. Arians. Nestorians.</note> ſixteene ſeuerall ſortes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe: but what followed? Firſt, <hi>Choſroes</hi> king of the Perſians ſacked Ieruſalem, and much weakened the Empire: Then, (<hi>Heraclius</hi> the Emperour turned Monothelite) <hi>Mahomet</hi> that infernall monſter, being made the Captaine of the Saracens, tooke Syria and Aegypt, Anno Dom 635. Meſopotamia, An. Dom. 639. and afterward all Africa: Finally we thinke that in the reuolution of the fifteene firſt ages, the Nation or kingdome cannot be named, which forſaking the catholike Romane religion, or not keeping it whole, and inuiolated, was either not conquered, or miſerably torne by ciuill diuiſion and ſlaughters.</p>
            <p>31. A religion, whoſe profeſſant companie or congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath bene euermore ſince the firſt planting thereof, very viſible and perſpicuous; as the ſeuerall reſemblances, parables and figuratiue ſpeeches, vſed in holy Scripture, doe cleerely teſtifie, that the true Church and Spouſe of Chriſt ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be, comparing her to a <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 18. 5.</note> 
               <hi>tabernacle placed in the Sunne:</hi> to a <note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>mountaine prepared in the toppe of mountaines:</hi> to a <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 5. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Citie, ſcituated on a hill:</hi> to a <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 3. 12. Luke 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Floore:</hi> to a <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 13. 47.</note> 
               <hi>Nette:</hi> a <note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Sheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde:</hi> a <note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 14. 16.</note> 
               <hi>great Supper:</hi> a <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 21. 33. Luke 20. 9.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard &amp;c.</hi> and her doctrine to a <note n="i" place="margin">Matth 5. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Candle put vpon a candleſticke, ſhining to all that are in the houſe,</hi> that is, in the world, as <note n="k" place="margin">Tract 2. in epiſt. Ioan.</note> S. <hi>Auſten</hi> vnderſtandeth the place: things that are all, moſt viſible and obuious to weakeſt ſenſe, and therefore doe proue, that the true Church ought to be alwayes viſible, and apparant to the view of others. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the word [<hi>Church</hi>] to be found throughout the whole body of Scripture, to ſignifie other then a viſible knowne mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: and the reaſon is plaine, why it muſt ſo ſignifie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it were otherwiſe impoſſible for any one, to ioyne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the true Church, perſeuere therein, obey the head, and be ſubiect to the Prelates thereof, (which all are bound to doe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8085:21"/> by the expreſſe word of God, lawe of nature, and vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uieſt<note place="margin">Matth. 18. 17. Epheſ. 5. 23. Hebr. 13. 17.</note> curſe and cenſure of damnation) if the Church were, or could be inuiſible, or not remonſtrable. For vnto things hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den &amp; inuiſible, there can be no repaire, no adherence, nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of duetie, or tribute of obedience defrayed.</p>
            <p>Nay, to deny the perpetuall viſibilitie, and duration of the Church, were in great parte to euacuate Chriſtes paſſion, and plainely to robbe him of the ende he ſuffered for: namely, to <hi>ſanctifie and cleanſe his Church,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 26.</note> 
               <hi>it glorious vnto him:</hi> It were (<hi>the Church being,</hi> as the ſame<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 23.</note> Apoſtle writeth, <hi>Chriſts bodie and the fulneſſe of him</hi>) to make Chriſt a head bodyleſſe, and take, as it were, his totalitie or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from him: it were, to diuorce our Sauiour from his dearely beloued ſpouſe formed out of his ſide vpon the croſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 29.</note> and inſeparably ioyned in marriage with him: it were, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue his omnipotent Maieſtie of <hi>his houſe, kingdome, lotte and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim 315. Coloſ. 1. 14. Pſal. 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>heritage vpon earth:</hi> for ſuch is his Church vnto him, and ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in holy Scripture: yea, It were, directly to charge the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Apoſtles, and euen Chriſt himſelfe, either with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueths, or abſurdities: The Prophets; becauſe theſe words are read in <hi>Eſay: Thy gates</hi> (ſpeaking to the future church of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians)<note place="margin">Eſa. 60. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be open continually, neyther day nor night ſhall they be ſhutte, that the ſtrength of the Gentiles and their Kings may bee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ca. 61. 8.</note> 
               <hi>brought vnto thee.</hi> And in another place; <hi>I the Lord will make an euerlasting couenant with them, and their ſeede ſhall be knowne among the Gentiles, and their branches in the midst of people. All that ſee them, ſhall know them, that they are the ſeede which our Lord hath bleſſed.</hi> What could be plainer ſpoken for proofe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the viſibilitie or perpetuitie of Chriſtes Church? <hi>her gates</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall be open continually, ſhut neyther by day nor night; and that God hath made an euerlasting couenant with her,</hi> and that <hi>all that ſee her children ſhal know them,</hi> and know, <hi>that our Lorde hath bleſſed them.</hi> The Apoſtles; becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to <hi>Timothie,</hi> teacheth him <hi>how he ought to conuerſe in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>houſe of God,</hi> ſo tearming the Church of God: nowe if the Church were inuiſible, the inſtruction muſt needes bee vayne
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8085:22"/> and abſurd; for none can conuerſe in an inuiſible houſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, S. <hi>Luke</hi> writeth, that <hi>the holy Ghoſt placed Biſhops in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20. 28</note> 
               <hi>Church of God, to rule the ſame:</hi> but who can rule a flocke, that is either inuiſible or vnknowne? Chriſt himſelfe; becauſe he promiſed his Apoſtles <hi>to remayne with them all dayes to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 28. 20.</note> 
               <hi>of the world:</hi> Which promiſe being made to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, was made to a viſible Church: and for that they were not (being mortall) to liue to the worldes ende, the promiſe was vndoubtedly made, to them, and their Succeſſors in their perſons: and therefore the Church neither euer to ceaſe or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inuiſible.</p>
            <p>Neither can the reaſons and places precedent be auoyded, by the ignorant diſtinction of a viſible and inuiſible Church,<note place="margin">A fantaſticall apprehenſion of <hi>Wicliffe</hi> and his followers, <hi>Waldenſ. to. 1. lib. 2. ca. 8. &amp; 9.</hi>
               </note> vnderſtanding by the latter, the hidde and vnknowne congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Predeſtinate: becauſe the Church, beeing a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of men, (as all writers affirme) and euery ſocietie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of neceſſitie ſome viſible ſigne, badge, ceremonie, bond, rite, profeſſion, inrollement, or ſome other like ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the members of the ſame may bee knowne, one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and alſo from others; which eſſentiall point failing in the company of the predeſtinate, they can no way poſſibly make vp the realitie, name or nature of a Church. For as <hi>S. Auſten</hi>
               <note place="margin">Contra Fauſt. lib. 19. cap. 11.</note> truely writeth, <hi>In nullum nomen religionis, ſeu verum, ſeu falſum, coagulari homines poſſunt, niſi aliquo ſignaculorum vel Sacramento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum viſibilium conſortio colligentur.</hi> Men cannot be incorporate in any one name of Religion, eyther falſe or true, vnleſſe they be combyned together by ſome communitie, or participation of viſible ſeales or Sacraments.</p>
            <p>Againe, this hidde and vnknowne predeſtinate company, which muſt bee thought to conſtitute an inuiſible Church, doe eyther refuſe, or not refuſe to communicate with the falſe and adulterous church in eccleſiaſticall ſubiection, ſeruice, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and externall worſhippe: If they doe refuſe, then is their company and church not inuiſible, but moſt viſible and markable: and of the other ſide, if they doe not refuſe, then ſith the falſe Church is by teſtimonie of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 2. 9.</note>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:8085:22"/> 
               <hi>Synogogue of Sathan,</hi> and her doctrine <note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the doctrine of diuels;</hi> they muſt needes bee guiltie of damnable ſinne by ſuch their partaking with her. And therefore their company not Gods Church, becauſe that multitude cannot poſſibly bee Gods church, wherein there are none <note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 27. <hi>Aug. contr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſt. poſt Col. cap. 20. &amp; de doctr. Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sti lib. 3. cap. 34. &amp; Retract. lib. 2. cap. 18. &amp; epiſt. 48. ad Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</hi>
               </note> good, but all wicked diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, and clokers of their faith. <hi>With the heart</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 10. 10</note> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) wee beleeue vnto iuſtice, but with the mouth</hi> (vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereby all external actions) <hi>confeſſion is made to ſaluation.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle biddeth all men <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 16. 17. Tit. 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>to auoyde falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> and <note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 6. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſeparate themſelues from them:</hi> yea <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh 10. 5.</note> 
               <hi>not to follow them, but to flee from them,</hi> is a marke which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelfe giueth, of diſtinguiſhing his true ſheepe from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Wee would ſay by that is ſayde, that perpetuall viſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being an eſſentiall qualitie and note of Gods church, and euer really exiſting with vs, and in our religion, (as all ſortes of teſtimonies in the world doe witneſſe) and in no other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany or congregation ſoeuer: it followeth, that our church is the ſole true church and ſpouſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>32. A religion, in whoſe largeneſſe and ſpreading ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ouer the whole world, the predictions and promiſe of our Sauiour are verified, nor can take their trueth and verification in any other ſect or doctrine that euer was, or is at this day on earth. <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 24. 14.</note> 
               <hi>This Goſpell of the kingdome</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>ſhall be preached in the whole world for a teſtimonie to all nations.</hi> And by the penne of another Euangeliſt, <note n="i" place="margin">Luke 24. 47.</note> 
               <hi>That penance ſhould be preached in his Name, and remiſſion of ſinnes vnto all Nations.</hi> And our Lord alſo compared <hi>this his Goſpell to</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 13. 31. Mark. 4. 32.</note> 
               <hi>a Muſtard ſeede,</hi> one of <hi>the leaſt of all ſeedes in the beginning, but when it is growen, it maketh great boughes, ſo that the byrds of the ayre</hi> (that is, as Expoſitors interprete, the greateſt Powers, and the moſt wiſe of the world) <hi>come, and dwell vnder the ſhadowe thereof,</hi> making their reſidence, happineſſe, and reſt therein: A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, and predictions, which cannot agree or fall in with any other religion, ſaue onely with the catholike Romane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and with this very fully, as the particulars precedent, and ſubſequent doe cleerely demonſtrate.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:8085:23"/>
            <p>33. A religion, that hath alwayes had (as the Apoſtle aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth Gods Church ſhould euer haue, yeelding alſo foure weightie cauſes of the ſame) a perpetuall viſible continuance of knowne <hi>Paſtors and Doctors, to the conſummation of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Saincts,</hi> the firſt cauſe: <hi>vnto the worke of the ministery,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe: <hi>vnto the edifying of the body of Chriſt,</hi> the third cauſe: <hi>that now we be not children wauering, and caried about with euery winde of doctrine,</hi> the fourth cauſe: and this, <hi>vntill we meete all into the vnitie of faith,</hi> that is, to the worlds end. Which ſucceſſiue and euer continuing duration of <hi>Paſtors and Doctors</hi> (the ſame being alſo promiſed before to the true chriſtian Church by ſeuerall <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 88. 31. &amp; ſequ. Eſa. 59 20. &amp; 21. Ierem. 31. 31. &amp; ſequ. Ezech. 37. 25.</note> Prophets, and ſo greatly materiall in it ſelfe, as without it, there can be no Church (as both <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. 4. epiſt. 9.</note> 
               <hi>S. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> and <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. contr. Luciferian.</note> 
               <hi>S. Hierome</hi> do abſolutely affirme) hath not, nor can be euer proued to haue bene fulfilled in any other Church, ſaue only in the Catholike Romane Church: and in it, moſt apparantlie demonſtrable by the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories of all ages, and by the ſhort ſpace, or rather momentarie blaſt of time that all other religions compared with ours, haue indured.</p>
            <p>34. A religion, whoſe doctrine is to be traced euen vp to the Apoſtles chaire, by true and lawfull ſucceſſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, euery one of them holding vnitie with his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and keeping ſtill, as the Apoſtle directeth, the <hi>depoſitum</hi> that deſcended from hand to hand vnto them. Which vnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted line of ſucceſſion, neuer leaping ouer the head of any one age, or yeare, and drawing his originall from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, can not but neceſſarily proue, that our Church is only the true Apoſtolicall Church, and that we <hi>continue and contend</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1. 23. phil. 3. 16. &amp; iude verſ. 3.</note> (as we are commanded) <hi>in and for the faith which was firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</hi> And it is alſo euident by the irrefragable authoritie of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> that the Romanes had once the true faith, affirming (<hi>d) their faith to be renowmed in the whole world, and common to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 8. &amp; cap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>him and them.</hi> Likewiſe it is euident by the vniforme report of all Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories, and by the writings of all the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8085:23"/> Fathers <note n="a" place="margin">Theodoretus in ca. 16. epiſt. ad Rom. Proſp. car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine de ingr. in principi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. S. Leo de N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Petri. Aug. contr. epiſt. Fund. ca. 4. Oroſius lib. 7. ca. 6. Chriſoſt. in Pſal. 88. Epiph. har. 27. Prud. in hym. 2. S. Laurentij. &amp; hym. 12. Optatus lib. 2. contr. Donatiſt. Ambr. lib. 5. epiſt. de baſilicis tradendis. Hiero. in Catalogo. Lactantius lib. 4. ca 21. de vera Sapien. Euſebius hiſt. Eccle. li. 2. ca. 13. 15. Athanaſ. de fugaſua. Cipria. epiſt. 55. nu. 6. Tert. de praeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. nu. 4. &amp; li. 4. Contr. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio. nu. 4. Origin. in Gen. apud Euſeb. lib. 3. ca. 1. Irenaus lib. 3. ca. 3. Hegeſippus lib. 3. ca. 2. de Excid. Hieroſolym. Caius, Papias, &amp; Dioniſ. Epiſco. Corinth. citati per Euſeb. lib. 2. ca. 14. &amp; 24. Ignat. epiſt. ad Rom. Concil. Calced. act. 3. and others.</note> Greeke and Latine, yea and by the very ſence and ſight of ſundrie monuments yet extant, that <hi>S. Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſuffred death there, and was the firſt Biſhop of that See. Now if our Counterplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders can ſufficientlie ſhew (as we are ſure the whole world cannot) either that the <hi>Romanes</hi> haue ſince that time left the faith which <hi>S. Paul</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in them, or that any of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Biſhops to <hi>S. Peter</hi> in that See, haue changed the firſt faith by paring away any part thereof, or by adding any new doctrine contrarie to the rule of the former, or what was not taught before by the Fathers, and after expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiuely added as a more cleare and particular declaration of the ſame: if this, we ſay, can be ſufficientlie ſhewed, by naming the Pope or other man, who in ſuch ſort changed the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue faith, and the point or points of faith that were ſo changed, together with the time and place, when and where the change was firſt made, we yeeld our ſelues to be prophane Nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, yea Heretikes, and moſt worthie of the fagot.</p>
            <p>35. A religion, whoſe doctrine ſo generallie ſymboliſeth, and holdeth the like abſolute conſent with all parts of holie Scripture that were euer receiued of the Chriſtian world: with the decrees of all confirmed Oecumenicall Counſels, and with the ioint aſſertions of all auntient Fathers: as ſhe is not driuen like <note n="b" place="margin">The Lutheran, and Caluiniſt reiect Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch, Tobie, Iudith, the booke of Wiſdom, Eccleſiaſticus, the Machabees, certaine Chapters of Eſther, the laſt part of Daniel. And the Lutherans the Epiſtle of S. Iames, S. Paul to the Hebrews, the Epiſtle of Saint Iude, the ſecond of Saint Peter, the ſecond and third of Saint Iohn.</note> other Religions for defending her poſitions, to reiect ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture, Councell, or the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme opinion of Doctors, but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the approbation of her doctrine from them all, and teacheth all her children out of <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Epiſt. 118. ca. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putare contra id quod tota per orbem
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8085:24"/> frequentat eccleſia inſolentiſſimae dementiae eſt,</hi> To call the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of that into queſtion, which the whole Church fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenteth throughout the world is moſt inſolent madneſſe.</p>
            <p>36. A religion which no perſecution coulde any time vanquiſh, nor the conioyned forces, malice, and machination of Pagan, Iewe, or other her moſt powrefull enemies, nor yet that which is infinitely of far more force to this end, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked liues of ſeuerall her profeſſors and chiefe rulers either haue hitherto, or ſhall to the worlds end (as we aſſuredly beleeue) euer be able to extirpate it wholie, or ſo to darken the viſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or beautie thereof, as to make it no where to appeere, or not to ſhine. Nay, God hath alwayes bin ſo ſtrong on her ſide, as the more ſhe was perſecuted, the more ſhe multiplied. An obſeruation that long ſince cauſed <note n="a" place="margin">In Tryphone.</note> 
               <hi>Iustinus</hi> to reſemble our Churches perſecution to the pruning of Vines, which maketh them the more fertile, and likewiſe moued <note n="b" place="margin">Cap. vlt. Apologetici.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> to call the bloud of her Martyrs the ſeed of Chriſtians, one dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and many riſing thereof. Neither can it be well doubted, but that if our religion (to ſpeake with <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 5. 39.</note> wiſe <hi>Gamaliel</hi>) had bin of men, and not of God, it would haue bin diſſolued long ere this, as all other ſects haue periſhed in much ſhorter while, agreeablie to the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule,</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">2. Tim 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall proſper no farther,</hi> and to that of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Petr. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Their perdition ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth not.</hi> Sith therefore our Church is not only not ſunck, or obſcured by any might, or neuer ſo violent ſtormes of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, but rather as the Arck of <hi>Noe,</hi> the greater the deluge and waues, the higher, and more illuſtriouſlie ſhe mounteth, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that of all others ſhe muſt be that very Church, againſt which by the promiſe of our Sauiour, <note n="f" place="margin">Math. 16. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Hell gates,</hi> (that is, the power and hatred of man, and deuill) <hi>ſhall not preuaile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>37. A religion, ſome of whoſe Profeſſours haue had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vpon euery neede occurring, power and grace to caſt out diuels of the bodies of the poſſeſſed; the firſt of all other ſignes, which our Sauiour himſelfe gaue, for hauing his true<note place="margin">Mar. vlt. v. 17.</note> beleeuers diſtinguiſhed from others. And this gifte is ſo well knowne, by continuall execution thereof, to reſide in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8085:24"/> catholike church, and neuer found in the companies of any other Profeſſions, as there needeth no recitall of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> Pope of late memorie, diſpoſſeſſed <hi>tactu</hi>
               <note place="margin">Onuphrius de vita Pij quint.</note> 
               <hi>ſtolae, &amp; data benedictione;</hi> onely by touch of his ſtole, and by giuing his benediction. And how frequent theſe effectes, not onely vpon perſons poſſeſſed, but in driuing away diuels alſo from the places they moſt infeſtuouſly haunted, haue bin euen newly wrought in both the Indies, where no other religion profeſſing Chriſt, is knowne, but the catholike Romane reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion onely: <hi>Petrus Martyr, Gonzalus Ouetanus,</hi> in their hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Indies, and <hi>Gonzalus Mendoza</hi> in his hiſtorie of China, doe giue moſt ample teſtimonie.</p>
            <p>38. Finally, a religion, (that we deſcend to no more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars) which by more meanes, and ſtronger then any other kinde of religion, keepeth, by the nature of her doctrine and holy ordinances, the ſubiectes in due allegeance to their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Lordes; teaching that <note n="a" place="margin">D. Tho. 1. 2. q. 96. art. 4. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Epheſ. to. 4. ca. 16. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ltano interpr.</note> the iuſt lawes of Princes do binde in conſcience, and ſome kindes alſo of vniuſt lawes vpon feare of ſcandall; and likewiſe decreeing <note n="b" place="margin">Concil. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. 5. ca. 1. &amp; Concil. Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſe ca. 14. &amp; 15.</note> that all ſuch as moue ſedition againſt their Soueraigne, or obſtinately im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne or diſobey his lawfull commandements, ſhould be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently excommunicated, and all the faithfull debarred to keepe them companie. And a religion, which hath euermore bleſſed the kings, that were her louers and children, with more peace, with more loue of their ſubiectes, with more proſperitie, with moe victories, with more true glory, with more temporall and eternall renowne, then other Princes, who were her enemies, or aliens, at any time attained to; as the regiſters of former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the memorials of the preſent, are moſt cleere and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Nor are theſe (ô moſt gratious Soueraigne) the onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes, that thus embolden vs to become humble ſuiters at your Highneſſe foote, for toleration of catholike religion; but our manifolde dangers vnder-gone, our ſeuerall loſſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities ſuſtained, and the ſtore of catholike blood that hath beene ſhedde, for affecting your mothers Rightes and Title,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8085:25"/> and for ſeeking how to ſuccour her piteous diſtreſſes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (the worthieſt Queene that many ages enioyed, liuing a long impriſoned Confeſſor, &amp; dying a moſt glorious Martir,) ſerue alſo to pleade and crie to your Maieſtie, for commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our caſe, and graunt of the Petition we make. And as our true loue, zeale and tribute of ſeruice, did not then dilate and extend it ſelfe onely towardes your Highneſſe deare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but in and through her, reached alſo to your ſacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; ſo ſince the time of her happie Crowne of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, our wiſhes, indeuours and actions, haue euer leuelled, as much as lay in our power, to the moſt aduancing of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Title. Yea, the preſſures and afflictions loaded on vs for this cauſe, were in a ſorte comfortable, or not diſcomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto vs, in hope of the relaxation and eaſe, wee aſſuredly expected by your Highneſſe actuall arriuall to the Crowne. So that now, if your excellent Maieſtie may not be moued, to permit the free exerciſe of the catholike Religion, Oh, our hopes fedde on, are not onely fruſtrate, and our long expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vaine; but our temporall lottes, by reeſtabliſhing of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lawes againſt vs, become more abiect, ſeruile, deſperate and forlorne, then euer before.</p>
            <p>Puritaniſme differing from Proteſtancie in 32. articles of doctrine, (as their owne bookes and writings doe witneſſe) looketh vp, ſpreadeth, and is neither ſuppreſſed with penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor oppreſſed with indignities, but her profeſſors receiue grace, and holde high authoritie in the gouernement: onely the catholike religion (whoſe profeſſors ſuffred moſt for your good Mothers ſake, and euer leaſt offended your Maieſtie) is deſpiſed, troden vnder foote, maligned, puniſhed, and muſt be, alas, by all violence aboliſhed, without regard of her vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable antiquitie, or reſpect of the large dominions ſhee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where hath to her dowery, or of the innumerable conqueſts ſhee hath made ouer all other Sectes, from Chriſtes time hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, or of the multitude and impregnableneſſe of her proofes, which her profeſſors are ready, yea, preſſe, and doe moſt earneſtly long to bring in publike Diſpute, for teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8085:25"/> of the doctrine ſhe teacheth. And that which mooueth not the leaſt admiration herein, is; for that neither the inward beleefe of the catholike Romane faith, nor the outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or defence thereof in wordes, ſeeme to bee the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions which are ſo ſharpely animaduerted; but rather the onely fault which is puniſhed, and neuer ſufficiently, as ſome thinke, puniſhed in vs, is the vndiſſembled profeſſion of our inward faith, in refuſing to goe to the Proteſtant church: A neceſſitie, which vnder guilt of deadly ſinne, and breach of our churches vnitie, all are bound vnto, that beleeue the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the catholike religion, and purpoſe ſtill to keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues her children: bicauſe the vnity therof conſiſteth in the <note n="a" place="margin">Aug. de doctr. Chriſtian. lib. 3. cap. 6. &amp; epist. 118. cap. 1. &amp; Baſil. in exhort. ad baptiſm.</note> connexion of the members together, by an externall reuerence and vſe of the ſame ſeruice and ſacraments, and is broken by hauing communion in either, with any other contrary religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And it is an axiome among all Diuines, that <note n="b" place="margin">Aug. de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. Eccleſ. cont. Petil. ep. cap 2. &amp; contr. lit. Peti. lib. 2. cap. 38 &amp; in Euangel. Ioan. tract. 118. &amp; in ſer. ſup. geſt. cum Emerito vltra med. &amp; epiſt. 152. Cypr. de Simplic. Praelatorum.</note> 
               <hi>extra ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam non eſt ſalus:</hi> there is no hope of ſaluation out of the church. To which <hi>Lactantius</hi> moſt plainely ſubſcribeth, ſaying; <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 4. cap. vlt. diui. Inſtit.</note> 
               <hi>Sola eccleſia catholica est templum dei, quo ſi quis non intraue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, vel à quo ſi quis exierit, à ſpe vitae ac ſalutis aeternae alienus est.</hi> The catholike church is onely the temple of God, into which if any ſhall not enter, or out of which if any ſhall depart, he is an alien from hope of life and eternall ſaluation. Neither do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Apoſtle affirme leſſe in ſenſe, where he ſaith, that <note n="d" place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt is the Sauiour of his bodie,</hi> and that <note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 23. Epheſ. 4 5. &amp; Cantic. 6. 8.</note> 
               <hi>the Church is his bodie.</hi> Nor is it poſſible to be conceiued in any vnderſtanding that two ſuch repugnant and contradictorie manners of ſeruing God, (there being <hi>but one Lord, one trueth, one faith, one Church</hi>) as the Catholike and Proteſtant obſerue in their churches, can be both, good, or not one of them, very vngodly, and in no caſe to be communicated with, vnder paine of eternall damnation.</p>
            <p>By the little which is ſaide, your princely Wiſedome may eaſily perceiue, that our abſtayning from Church, is in vs no formall act of diſobedience, much leſſe of ſelfe-wilfulneſſe or contempt of your Maieſties lawes, (aſperſions, with which, many would diſtaine our refuſall) but a true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eall obligation of meere conſcience, eſpecially for ſo long, as wee holde the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8085:26"/> perſwaſion we doe: in reſpect an erroneous conſcience<note place="margin">Rom. 14. 14. &amp; 23. <hi>Chriſoſt. hom. 26. in ep. ad R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. &amp; eſt ſententia com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nis omnium Thelogorum in 2 Diſt. 30. &amp; D Tho. 1. 2. qu. 10. art. 5.</hi>
               </note> bindeth as ſtrongly, and vnder equall payne, as doth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that is beſt and moſt rightly informed.</p>
            <p>To drawe to an ende; wee moſt ſubmiſſiuely beſeech your Maieſtie, to conceaue no otherwiſe of vs, then of your moſt dutifull and loyall vaſſals: acknowledging in all politike and ciuill affaires, no other Superior then the ſacred authoritie of your Highneſſe, and reſting euer moſt ready to accompliſh all your commandements touching the ſame, were our liues neuer ſo certainely engaged in the execution; Onely requeſting, that in matters of ſoule and conſcience, we may haue leaue, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh an eternall Lorde, from a temporall Lorde, and to preferre our obedience to the one before our obedience to the other, if obedience to Princes, againſt God, may bee tearmed obedience; and not rather irreligious puſillanimitie. And as wee haue preſumed (moſt pretious Soueraigne) vpon confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of your true royall diſpoſition and benignitie, to make knowne to your Princely conſideration and wiſedome our griefes, our hopes, the fauour and conniuence we deſire, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome fewe reaſons, aſwell of ſtate as of religion, for ſhewing the concordaunce that our requeſt hath with the good of ſtate, and alſo the groundes of our perſwaſion in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, why the religion we beleeue in, is true: So do we car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a moſt tender regarde of yeelding all ſatisfaction to your Maieſtie, and to all other in authoritie, yea, euen to thoſe who ſtand moſt iealouſly conceited of the true affection and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Prieſtes, (the Paſtours of our ſoules) towardes your Highneſſe perſon, Crowne, and the weale of the Realme. In whoſe behalfe, we doe therefore confidently and moſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly vndertake, that they all ſhal willingly &amp; readily take their corporall oathes, for continuing their true alleageance to your Maieſty and the State: or in caſe that be not thought aſſurance enough, they ſhall giue in ſufficient ſuerties, one or moe, who ſhall ſtand bound, life for life, for the performance of the ſaid alleageance, and of their fidelitie and faithfulneſſe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes. Yea, they moſt voluntarily offer yet further, that if ſo any of their number bee not able to put in ſuch ſecuritie for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8085:26"/> their loyall cariages, that then they will all ioyne in one ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the Pope, for recalling ſuch prieſtes out of the Land, whoſoeuer they be, or how many ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>We feare to be tedious, and therefore we will ſhut vp all in few words. Our harts, our ſoules, and both, with deepeſt cries do moſt humblie and alike inſtantlie beſeech your moſt excellent Maieſtie to take pitie of our afflictions, to compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate our ſufferings, and to relieue our long indured preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, either by licenſing the free vſe of our Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; or if we may not be ſo happie, yet at leaſt by granting a publike Diſputation, to the end we may be heard, our cauſe tryed, and our teachers receiue confutation, and the deſerued ſhame of their falſe doctrine, if in caſe they haue miſled vs. A fauour which the aduerſaries of our religion haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in other Countries, and which our Country-oppoſitors ſeeme in their bookes to be very deſirous of, and is alſo of it ſelfe, of all other meanes, the moſt potent, to reunite all parties in one, the deceiued being hereby let to ſee their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. So that by the graunt thereof, no doubt your Maieſtie ſhall get eternall praiſe ouer the Chriſtian world, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant religion euerlaſting fame if ſhe preuaile; the neighbour countries great edification; the wauerers, and ſuch as are doubtfull in faith, a ſtay and worthie ſatisfaction as none greater; all poſteritie a right noble example and preſident to follow: And we your Maieſties loyall ſubiects muſt and ſhall alwayes, as our bounden dutie exacteth, reſt, through the deliuery out of the blindnes (if ſo wee liue in blindnes) for euer moſt ſtrictly oblieged to pray inceſſantly for your Highneſſe long life, and proſperous raigne ouer all your Dominions, with multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of immortall renowne in this world, and of endles ioyes in the next.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:8085:27"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> line 26. for, to impugne, reade do impugne. Page 14. in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Francis Dominik,</hi> reade <hi>Francis, Dominik.</hi> Page 36. line 27. for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 30, reade daily, go.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8085:27"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
